<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>odl</title>
    <link>/rss.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2019 </copyright>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 14:09:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Joseph Houck</title>
      <link>/team-directory/joseph</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/joseph</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Louis Leblond</title>
      <link>/spotlight/louis</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ This is Louis spotlight page. ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/spotlight/louis</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Louis Leblond</title>
      <link>/team-directory/louis</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Louis Leblond is the Director of Online Education in Physics and a Lecturer of
  Physics in the Eberly College of Science. He is also the first Tombros Fellow
  for Digital Learning. The Tombros Fellow of Digital Learning is a 1-year
  position and is responsible for the following:
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  <li>
    Exploring new technologies for teaching practices by conceiving of,
    consulting on, and implementing new digital projects;
  </li>
  <li>
    Considering research-based practices and potential mechanisms for assessment
    of the impacts digital technologies on student learning;
  </li>
  <li>
    Sharing digital learning technologies and ideas by engaging with faculty in
    the college;
  </li>
  <li>
    Working on public-facing projects, in resident instruction, world campus, or
    outreach projects, with potential for demonstrable benefits to students and
    ECoS;
  </li>
</div>
<div>
  <br />
  Louis is working on creating an online version of PHYS 211 Mechanics and PHYS
  212 Electrogmagnetism using a new tool called the IOLab, a multifunctional
  measuring device for physics labs.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Dr. Leblond's other interests include:
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Online education, with a focus on developing (and assessing the efficacy) of
  new innovative learning tools in online education.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Theoretical cosmology with particular emphasis on inflation, cosmic strings,
  dark matter and dark energy.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  High energy physics: string theory, quantum gravity and physics beyond the
  standard model with particular interests in the subjects of de Sitter
  spacetime and time-dependent backgrounds.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/louis</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H5P - Documentation Tool</title>
      <link>/blog-posts/11-19-18</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>Are you searching for a creative, interactive, and engaging way to have
    students submit details about an
    assignment or project they’re working on? Would you like this information to
    be exported to a nicely
    formatted text document instantly? Look no further! H5P’s Documentation Tool
    allows you to create a
    project outline complete with instructions and assessment possibilities. In
    this video, I set up a simple
    demonstration that identifies some basic goals while also asking users to
    supply their insight as they traverse
    through each step. Specifically, we look over the general settings of the
    tool and work through building an
    example that will help users scaffold out a detailed steps-to-completion
    outline, create a plan of attack, and
    organize / assess individual goals and contributions. At the end, we'll
    review the different ways we can
    implement this newly created content into your website. Check it out!
</div>
<div>
    <br> 
    <video-player lang="en" preload="metadata"
        source="https://youtu.be/8-PdyiAkkuI"
        sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="8-PdyiAkkuI" iframed
        source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media is-youtube media-title="H5P -
        Documentation Tool"></video-player>
</div> ]]>
      </description>
      <category>H5P,Content,Engagement</category>
      <guid>/blog-posts/11-19-18</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charles Lavera</title>
      <link>/team-directory/chuck</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  My name is Charles Lavera; I am a Multimedia Specialist / Web Developer with
  the Office of Digital Learning (ODL) at the Eberly College of Science at Penn
  State. Originally from the Pittsburgh area, I uphold a broad background in
  digital-media and web-development with a focus on Drupal-installations, web
  component architecture, interactive content (H5P), and open-source technology.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  You could say that I wear many hats, but I consider my flexibility to be my
  greatest asset as I am able to provide support in a number of areas when
  needed. My favorite part of working with the ODL team has been the opportunity
  to collaborate with faculty and staff to create engaging web-experiences that
  showcase innovation and modern web-advancements. From complete websites to
  custom course-applications, we have fun exploring the deepest recesses of our
  creativity while we build a better future.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Outside of the office, I am known for being a loving husband, dedicated
  musician, an avid hockey fan, and a nature enthusiast.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/chuck</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Michael Potter</title>
      <link>/team-directory/mike</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Michael is an educational technologist who brings a decade’s worth of
  experience building websites and applications to the edtech space. His
  non-traditional path began at Penn State where he earned his BA in Political
  Science. From there, Michael joined a local venture capital group where he was
  involved with many different companies and handled everything from sales, to
  product development, to logistics and shipping. When one such company lost
  their only web developer, Michael was tapped to takeover the programming
  responsibilities and the rest is history. Michael was immediately hooked with
  web development and begin soaking up every piece of information the web could
  offer.
<br/>
</div>
<div><br/></div>
<div>
  Since then, Michael has gained a wealth of experience in the full stack of web
  applications. His skillset is most notable in the area of front-end
  development and the Drupal framework. He has a passion for writing code,
  learning how to code, and mentoring fellow programmers. Michael has a unique
  gift for connecting, inspiring, and empowering others.
  <br/>
  <br/>
</div>
<div>
  Innovative, forward thinking, risk taking are some of the reasons Michael
  wanted to work at ODL. His goal is to create technology and applications that
  remove barriers between educators and students. Michael believes that the web
  can enable people to change their lives for the better.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/mike</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:23:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carly Dreibelbis</title>
      <link>/team-directory/carly</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  I have always been obsessed with visuals. When I was a kid I would go through
  my mom’s magazines, find an image I loved, check with my mom to make sure she
  didn’t need the article on the back, then clip it out and safely tuck it away
  in a flat, waxed-cardboard box under my bed - only to find out years later
  that my mom secretly snuck in my room and downsized my collection to keep it
  under control.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  These days, I apply my passion for visual arts to graphic design and
  photography. I soak up inspiration all around me, and still tear out magazine
  ads and tuck them away for reference. I strive to visually present the facts
  and discipline of science with creativity, quality, technology and whenever
  possible… a bit of humor. I am always looking for new ways to approach
  courses, graphics, and content to successfully visually communicate concepts
  with an audience.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  If I’m not behind a computer screen, you can find me outside with a camera by
  my side or in mad scientist mode in my kitchen - while tripping over a hungry
  cattle dog vacuum.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/carly</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiSc 003</title>
      <link>/syllabi/bisc003</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the bisc003 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/bisc003</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiSc 004</title>
      <link>/syllabi/bisc004</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>This is the bisc004 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/bisc004</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 11</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol11</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol11 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol11</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phys 211</title>
      <link>/syllabi/phys211</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the phys211 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/phys211</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiSc 002</title>
      <link>/syllabi/bisc002</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the bisc002 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/bisc002</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 120N</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol120n</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol120n syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol120n</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 133</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol133</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this the biol133 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol133</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 141</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol141</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol141 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol141</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 155</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol155</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol155 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol155</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 177</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol177</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol177 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol177</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bmmb 551</title>
      <link>/syllabi/bmmb551</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the bmmb551 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/bmmb551</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biol 110</title>
      <link>/syllabi/biol110</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the biol110 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/biol110</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astro 130</title>
      <link>/syllabi/astro130</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the astro130 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/astro130</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiSc 001</title>
      <link>/syllabi/bisc001</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>This is the bisc001 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/bisc001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astro 140</title>
      <link>/syllabi/astro140</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2 id="killswitch">Course Content</h2>
<p>
<p>The possible existence of life beyond Earth is one of the most fundamental questions relating the human race to the physical Universe around us. While considerations of extraterrestrial life were in the domains of philosophy and science fiction in the past, today we have considerable scientific knowledge that can be applied to the question. Advances in modern astronomy have dramatically improved our understanding of our cosmic surroundings: tracing the cosmic origins of biological molecules, direct evidence for planets around most stars (exoplanets), and a deeper understanding of planet formation have all emerged in the past generation.  Several fields -- geology, biochemistry, paleontology (fossils), evolutionary biology --  give insight (though not a complete understanding) on how life arose on Earth, and spacecraft travel provides constraints on life elsewhere in our Solar System. </p>

<p>The results from studies on Earth, the Solar System, and exoplanets across the Galaxy together indicate that the conditions for life are widespread in the Universe; extraterrestrial life has not been found yet, but does not seem implausible. Interstellar space travel between habitable planets, by humans or other beings, is exceedingly difficult but not physically impossible.   The course is thus rooted in modern science, but is connected to the long-standing philosophical question: Are we alone in the Universe? Today, this question is often embedded in science fiction (such as movies about aliens) and discussion about whether aliens have visited Earth.  Today, astronomical studies are leading the way in answering part of the question:  Earth-like planets seems to be extremely common.  But there is no evidence yet for life outside of Earth.</p>
</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/astro140</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 005</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem005</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>this is the chem005 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem005</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astro 120</title>
      <link>/syllabi/astro120</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>This is the astro120 syllabus.</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/astro120</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astro 011</title>
      <link>/syllabi/astro011</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>astro011 syllabus page</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/astro011</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>