<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>odl</title>
    <link>/rss.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2020 </copyright>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 15:41:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Faculty Spotlight: Louis Leblond</title>
      <link>/spotlight/louis</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>
  Louis Leblonde is the Director of Online Education in Physics. With a strong
  passion for all things education (research and online), he teaches large
  enrollment intro physics courses and has worked tirelessly to enhance them
  with engaging, accessible, and innovative materials.
</p>
<p>
  Louis excells in creating unique online course experiences to enrich
  face-to-face classes and currently he is working on developing a hands-on lab
  for future physics online courses.
</p>
<p>
  Specifically, Louis has filmed a number of creative instructional lab videos.
  The videos feature Louis performing a variety of experiments that would help
  students visualize difficult concepts online.
</p>
<p>
  Check out some of his
  <a
    href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9PnJRokt-Ow&list=PLBBCdKoDCnCBA6YR6q4hkMM4_jOza7BQJ"
    target="_blank"
    >videos</a
  >.
</p>
<p>
  Moreover, when Loius isn't pouring over his course materials for quality and
  effectiveness, he's working to create resources for fellow faculty to improve
  the college.
</p>
<p>
  For example, here is a helpful video Louis created recently to help faculty
  transition into Canvas during the Corona Virus outbreak.
</p>
<video-player
  accent-color="grey"
  iframed="iframed"
  is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media"
  is-youtube="is-youtube"
  lang="en"
  preload="metadata"
  source="https://youtu.be/zPwe8nMYCq0"
  source-type="youtube"
  sticky-corner="top-right"
  youtube-id="zPwe8nMYCq0"
  schema-resource-id="#ff04a88e-140c-185a-7bef"
  resource="#ff04a88e-140c-185a-7bef"
  prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org "
  sources="[]"
  tracks="[]"
></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category>Spotlight,Education,Learning</category>
      <guid>/spotlight/louis</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 13:46:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2020 Horizon Report</title>
      <link>/blog-posts/3-5-20</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>
  The 2020 Horizon Report has just been released, taking a look at what may be
  impacting teaching and learning in the future. This report is very important
  in the digital world as it helps stakeholders learn, plan, and act on
  initiatives or developments that may influence higher education. The report
  summarizes trends that are unfolding as we speak: Social, Technological,
  Economic, Higher Education, and Political. Additionally, it takes a look at
  emerging technologies and practices that will have significant impact on the
  future of postsecondary education.
</p>
<p>
  The Office of Digital Learning is familiar with many of these emerging
  technologies, including NGDLEs, AI, Analytics, and online education. We hope
  you have a moment or two to download and look at the report. As always, we are
  interested in your thoughts and ways you think we can have an impact on the
  future of higher education.
</p>
<worksheet-download title="2020 Educause Horizon Report" link="https://library.educause.edu/-/media/files/library/2020/3/2020horizonreport.pdf"></worksheet-download> ]]>
      </description>
      <category>Educause,Report,Higer Education</category>
      <guid>/blog-posts/3-5-20</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drupal Camp NJ: Progressively Decoupled Drupal for Everyone</title>
      <link>/blog-posts/2-10-20</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>
  Recently, the Office of Digital Learning (Eberly College of Science at Penn
  State) participated in the ninth consecutive
  <a href="https://www.drupalcampnj.org/" target="_blank">Drupal Camp NJ</a>
  , hosted at Princeton University. The weekend witnessed developers and
  industry professionals collaborating on a number of Drupal initiatives through
  informative presentations, networking opportunities, and engaging training
  sessions.
</p>
<p>
  Demonstrating their progress since Drupal Camp NJ 2019, the ODL team continued
  where they left off with their discussion on decoupling Drupal. Specifically,
  Michal Potter and I joined
  <a href="https://www.elmsln.org/" target="_blank">ELMS:LN</a> lead developer,
  Bryan Ollendyke (College of Arts and Architecture - Penn State) and Rebecca
  Goodman (Branch Chief, Web at U.S.
  <a href="https://www.archives.gov/" target="_blank"
    >National Archives and Records Administration</a
  >
  / NARA) to present work on web components.
</p>
<p>
  Web components are a set of web platform APIs that allow you to create custom,
  reusable, HTML tags to use in web pages and web apps. Because they’re built
  using web standards, they will work across all modern browsers and within any
  JavaScript library or framework that works with HTML. The team has been
  actively working to implement web components across a number of projects,
  including a custom suite of authoring tools (<a
    href="https://haxtheweb.org/"
    target="_blank"
    >HAX</a
  >
  ), Drupal, WordPress, Grav CMS and more.
</p>
<p>
  Bryan Ollendyke jump-started the conversation with a great introduction and
  Michael Potter and I showcased our implementation of web components across
  several custom web themes. The highlight of the talk was Rebecca Goodman
  announcing that her web team at NARA had started implementing web components
  into their work-flow by successfully placing a branding bar across several of
  their existing web properties.
</p>
<p>
  Overall, feedback was extremely positive. The audience contained a wide
  variety of technical backgrounds. Developers quickly understood how they could
  reduce technical debt across their projects, graphic designers saw how their
  interactions with Content Management Systems could be simplified, and project
  managers realized how this approach could reduce timelines of maintenance and
  enhancement across the board.
</p>
<p>
  Check out our presentation below and see how web components can revolutionize
  your next web project:
</p>
<video-player
  accent-color="grey"
  iframed="iframed"
  is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media"
  is-youtube="is-youtube"
  lang="en"
  preload="metadata"
  source="https://youtu.be/4MXqYGGpeD8"
  source-type="youtube"
  sticky-corner="top-right"
  youtube-id="4MXqYGGpeD8"
  schema-resource-id="#fbb77a1d-12dc-b794-1190"
  resource="#fbb77a1d-12dc-b794-1190"
  prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org "
  sources="[]"
  tracks="[]"
></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category>Decoupled,Headless,Webdev</category>
      <guid>/blog-posts/2-10-20</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Louis Leblond</title>
      <link>/team-directory/louis</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Louis Leblond is the Director of Online Education in Physics and a Lecturer of
  Physics in the Eberly College of Science. He is also the first Tombros Fellow
  for Digital Learning. The Tombros Fellow of Digital Learning is a 1-year
  position and is responsible for the following:
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  <li>
    Exploring new technologies for teaching practices by conceiving of,
    consulting on, and implementing new digital projects;
  </li>
  <li>
    Considering research-based practices and potential mechanisms for assessment
    of the impacts digital technologies on student learning;
  </li>
  <li>
    Sharing digital learning technologies and ideas by engaging with faculty in
    the college;
  </li>
  <li>
    Working on public-facing projects, in resident instruction, world campus, or
    outreach projects, with potential for demonstrable benefits to students and
    ECoS;
  </li>
</div>
<div>
  <br />
  Louis is working on creating an online version of PHYS 211 Mechanics and PHYS
  212 Electrogmagnetism using a new tool called the IOLab, a multifunctional
  measuring device for physics labs.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Dr. Leblond's other interests include:
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Online education, with a focus on developing (and assessing the efficacy) of
  new innovative learning tools in online education.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Theoretical cosmology with particular emphasis on inflation, cosmic strings,
  dark matter and dark energy.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  High energy physics: string theory, quantum gravity and physics beyond the
  standard model with particular interests in the subjects of de Sitter
  spacetime and time-dependent backgrounds.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/louis</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joseph Houck</title>
      <link>/team-directory/joseph</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Pellentesque in ipsum id orci porta dapibus. Quisque velit nisi, pretium ut
  lacinia in, elementum id enim. Donec sollicitudin molestie malesuada.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/joseph</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Get Decoupled at Drupal Camp NJ</title>
      <link>/blog-posts/2-6-19</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>
  This past weekend (February 1-3) the Office of Digital Learning (Eberly
  College of Science at Penn State) participated in the eighth consecutive
  <a href="https://www.drupalcampnj.org/" target="_blank">Drupal Camp NJ</a>



, hosted at Princeton University. The annual event brings
  developers and industry professionals from varying backgrounds and
  skill-levels together to share all things <a href="https://www.drupal.org/" target="_blank">Drupal</a>


 through engaging
  presentations, co-working sessions, and networking.
</p>
<p>
  This year there were a number of great discussions to get involved with, but
  one topic continued to dominate the conversation - decoupling Drupal.
  Decoupling Drupal essentially means separating Drupal’s front-end (theme
  layer) from it’s back-end (data/content layer) using a custom JavaScript
  framework. While there are still some discussions as to which framework is
  ‘best’ when decoupling Drupal, the general consensus is that the decoupled
  method is becoming an industry-wide movement.
</p>
<p>
  Jesus Manuel Olivas (Head of Products at <a href="https://weknowinc.com/" target="_blank">weKnow</a>

) showcased decoupling tools
  like <a href="http://www.gatsbyjs.org/" target="_blank">Gatsby</a>
 and <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/tome" target="_blank">Tome</a>
. These tools assist in creating static sites by
  decoupling Drupal’s theme and just using Drupal for content creation.
</p>
<p>
  Saurabh Chugh and Surendra Singh hosted a discussion, ‘Decoupling Patterns,
  Services and creating an enterprise level editorial experience’ where they
  also emphasized using decoupled applications to display content.
</p>
<p>
  Saurabh Chugh and Surendra Singh hosted a discussion, ‘Decoupling Patterns,
  Services and creating an enterprise level editorial experience’ where they
  also emphasized using decoupled applications to display content.
</p>
<p>
  Our team demonstrated decoupled development when Michal Potter and Charles
  Lavera joined ELMS:LN lead developer, Bryan Ollendyke (College of Arts and
  Architecture - Penn State) to present work on web components. Specifically,
  the trio discussed the tooling they use to quickly generate and publish their
  components onto the web (<a href="https://github.com/elmsln/wcfactory" target="_blank">WCFactory</a>
 / Drupal <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/webcomponents" target="_blank">webcomponents module</a>
). In
  addition, Bryan explored the future of content-authoring with a completely
  headless authoring experience called HAX.
</p>
<p>
  Get decoupled at Drupal Camp NJ and check out our presentation below, then use
  this link ---> and try <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/" target="_blank">HAX</a>
 for yourself!
</p>
<video-player accent-color="grey" iframed="iframed" is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media" is-youtube="is-youtube" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://youtu.be/nYYUDsI-qwY" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="nYYUDsI-qwY" schema-resource-id="#e2f10b12-ed54-1899-4a04" resource="#e2f10b12-ed54-1899-4a04" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]"></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category>Decoupled,Headless,Webdev</category>
      <guid>/blog-posts/2-6-19</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H5P - Documentation Tool</title>
      <link>/blog-posts/11-19-18</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>Are you searching for a creative, interactive, and engaging way to have
    students submit details about an
    assignment or project they’re working on? Would you like this information to
    be exported to a nicely
    formatted text document instantly? Look no further! H5P’s Documentation Tool
    allows you to create a
    project outline complete with instructions and assessment possibilities. In
    this video, I set up a simple
    demonstration that identifies some basic goals while also asking users to
    supply their insight as they traverse
    through each step. Specifically, we look over the general settings of the
    tool and work through building an
    example that will help users scaffold out a detailed steps-to-completion
    outline, create a plan of attack, and
    organize / assess individual goals and contributions. At the end, we'll
    review the different ways we can
    implement this newly created content into your website. Check it out!
</div>
<div>
    <br/> 
    <video-player lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://youtu.be/8-PdyiAkkuI" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="8-PdyiAkkuI" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="H5P -
        Documentation Tool" accent-color="grey" resource="#149cc203-4b4b-4be5-345d" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]" schema-resource-id="#149cc203-4b4b-4be5-345d"></video-player>
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category>H5P,Content,Engagement</category>
      <guid>/blog-posts/11-19-18</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charles Lavera</title>
      <link>/team-directory/chuck</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  My name is Charles Lavera; I am a Multimedia Specialist / Web Developer with
  the Office of Digital Learning (ODL) at the Eberly College of Science at Penn
  State. Originally from the Pittsburgh area, I uphold a broad background in
  digital-media and web-development with a focus on Drupal-installations, web
  component architecture, interactive content (H5P), and open-source technology.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  You could say that I wear many hats, but I consider my flexibility to be my
  greatest asset as I am able to provide support in a number of areas when
  needed. My favorite part of working with the ODL team has been the opportunity
  to collaborate with faculty and staff to create engaging web-experiences that
  showcase innovation and modern web-advancements. From complete websites to
  custom course-applications, we have fun exploring the deepest recesses of our
  creativity while we build a better future.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  Outside of the office, I am known for being a loving husband, dedicated
  musician, an avid hockey fan, and a nature enthusiast.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/chuck</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Michael Potter</title>
      <link>/team-directory/mike</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  Michael is an educational technologist who brings a decade’s worth of
  experience building websites and applications to the edtech space. His
  non-traditional path began at Penn State where he earned his BA in Political
  Science. From there, Michael joined a local venture capital group where he was
  involved with many different companies and handled everything from sales, to
  product development, to logistics and shipping. When one such company lost
  their only web developer, Michael was tapped to takeover the programming
  responsibilities and the rest is history. Michael was immediately hooked with
  web development and begin soaking up every piece of information the web could
  offer.
<br/>
</div>
<div><br/></div>
<div>
  Since then, Michael has gained a wealth of experience in the full stack of web
  applications. His skillset is most notable in the area of front-end
  development and the Drupal framework. He has a passion for writing code,
  learning how to code, and mentoring fellow programmers. Michael has a unique
  gift for connecting, inspiring, and empowering others.
  <br/>
  <br/>
</div>
<div>
  Innovative, forward thinking, risk taking are some of the reasons Michael
  wanted to work at ODL. His goal is to create technology and applications that
  remove barriers between educators and students. Michael believes that the web
  can enable people to change their lives for the better.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/mike</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:23:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carly Dreibelbis</title>
      <link>/team-directory/carly</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <div>
  I have always been obsessed with visuals. When I was a kid I would go through
  my mom’s magazines, find an image I loved, check with my mom to make sure she
  didn’t need the article on the back, then clip it out and safely tuck it away
  in a flat, waxed-cardboard box under my bed - only to find out years later
  that my mom secretly snuck in my room and downsized my collection to keep it
  under control.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  These days, I apply my passion for visual arts to graphic design and
  photography. I soak up inspiration all around me, and still tear out magazine
  ads and tuck them away for reference. I strive to visually present the facts
  and discipline of science with creativity, quality, technology and whenever
  possible… a bit of humor. I am always looking for new ways to approach
  courses, graphics, and content to successfully visually communicate concepts
  with an audience.
  <br />
  <br />
</div>
<div>
  If I’m not behind a computer screen, you can find me outside with a camera by
  my side or in mad scientist mode in my kitchen - while tripping over a hungry
  cattle dog vacuum.
</div>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/team-directory/carly</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 111</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem111</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  CHEM 111 is an introductory chemistry laboratory experience that gives
  students the opportunity to put into practice the essential principles
  utilized in a professional chemistry laboratory regarding topics relevant to
  CHEM 110.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>Upon successful completion of this course students will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Conduct experiments on topics relevant to CHEM 110 in a manner that is safe,
    economical, and environmentally friendly
  </li>
  <li>
    Perform fundamental laboratory manipulations
  </li>
  <li>
    Make accurate experimental observations
  </li>
  <li>
    Accurately record and interpret data
  </li>
  <li>
    Recognize sources of error in experiments and estimate their importance
  </li>
  <li>
    Plan and produce useful reports of laboratory work that meet acceptable
    standards of completeness, accuracy, clarity, and neatness
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a
      href="https://www.carolina.com/catalog/detail.jsp?prodId=581862"
      target="_blank"
      >PSU Experimental Chemistry Kit</a
    >
  </li>
  <li>LabArchives (email sent to you)</li>
  <li>Scientific Calculator (non-programmable)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Course Overview & Safety</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>"Finding Scientific Information” Module</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Uncertainty and Measurement & Faster, Plop, Plop, Fizz, Fizz</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Atomic Emission</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Physical and Chemical Changes</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>Determination of Water Hardness by Titration</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Bonding and properties of water</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>Work week for project proposal</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>No Investigation<br />Midterm Exam 1 (Weeks 1-7)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>Fundamentals of Chromatography</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>Investigating Chemical Reactions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>Single replacement reactions: Stoich and percent yield</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>Gases</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>Enthalpy of a Reaction Using Hess’s Law</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>No Investigation<br />Midterm Exam 2 (Weeks 10-14)</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Laboratory Investigations (75%)</h2>
<p>
  Each week, there will be an investigation to complete. All of the information
  will be provided on LabArchives. The first two weeks are considered a “dry”
  lab because there will not be an explicit experiment conducted. Most
  laboratory investigations will be worth 70 points and consist of three parts:
  notebook pages, post-lab worksheet, and a quiz. Each part is explained in more
  detail below. The deadline to submit all parts of the investigation for the
  week will be on Tuesday of the following week.
</p>
<h2>Notebook Pages (10 points)</h2>
<p>
  There will be a dedicated page in LabArchives for collecting raw data and
  recording procedural notes.
</p>
<h2>Post-lab Worksheet (50 points)</h2>
<p>
  After completing the investigation and collecting the data, you will complete
  a worksheet where you will analyze the data. Analysis may consist of
  performing calculations with the data, making graphs, and assessing accuracy
  and/or precision of results.
</p>
<h2>Quiz (10 points)</h2>
<p>
  The quiz associated with each laboratory investigation can be completed at
  anytime during the week on Canvas. You will have 20-mintues and up to two
  attempts (only the highest score will be kept). The quizzes will test your
  conceptual understanding of the investigation.
</p>
<p>
  All parts of the lab investigations will be due on Tuesdays by 11:59 pm and
  should be handed in on time. If they are not handed in on time, substantial
  penalties will apply (–10% for each day that an assignment is late). Material
  that is more than one week late will not be accepted.
</p>
<h2>Midterm Exams (10% each)</h2>
<p>
  There will be two (2) midterm exams given over the course of the semester.
  Exams are schedule on the following dates and times and will require you to
  come to campus. If you are not able to make the exam at that time, you must
  make arrangements with instructor for an alternate exam time earlier in the
  day.
</p>
<p>
  Exams will focus on material covered since the last exam; however, you are
  still responsible for information presented previously. The exams will consist
  of short answer questions and open-ended problems. Some questions may be
  multiple choice. Stay tuned to announcements for details on the format.
</p>
<h2>Participation (5%)</h2>
<p>
  We will have a class forum/chatroom for asking and answering questions about
  the course using Piazza (accessed in Canvas). You can ask and answer questions
  here, which will be monitored by the TA and instructor. Please direct your
  questions here before e-mailing. You will be able to ask and answer
  anonymously if you wish. The beauty of Piazza is that the entire class can
  benefit from the questions and answers. More information on enrolling and
  etiquette for using will be provided during the semester. You must make 10
  posts (questions or answers) anytime before October 19 to earn all 25
  participation points for the exam period. You will earn a proportionately
  lower score for fewer than 10 posts. Make an addition 10 posts (questions or
  answers) anytime between October 20 and December 7 to earn the remaining 25
  points.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<p>
  The final grade is calculated based on scores in each assignment category
  (details follow).
</p>
<table>
  <th>Activity</th>
  <th>Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Laboratory Investigations</td>
    <td>750</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Midterm Exams(2)</td>
    <td>100 each / 200 total</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Participation</td>
    <td>50</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Total</td>
    <td>1000</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>93-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>90-92%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>91-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>83-90%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>80-82%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>77-79%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>69-76%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>57-68%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>< 56%</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Make-up Exams</h2>
<p>
  As required by University regulations, students who miss an exam with a valid
  excuse (family emergency, illness, university-scheduled activities, etc.) will
  be given an opportunity to make-up the exam. Prearranged make ups can be taken
  earlier in the exam week. In order to be eligible for the make-up exam ALL of
  the following conditions MUST be fulfilled:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    The missed exam is the result of a University-approved excuse. Per Senate
    Policy 42-27, “Requests for missing class or an evaluative event due to
    reasons that are based on false claims may be considered violations of the
    policy on Academic Integrity”
  </li>
  <li>
    Instructor must be notified in writing (email is preferred) within 24 hours
    of the missed exam.
  </li>
  <li>
    You must schedule a make up for the exam within 1 week of the original exam
    date.
  </li>
</ol>
<h2>Regrades and Grade Corrections</h2>
<p>
  If after an exam or laboratory investigation is returned there is a question
  concerning the grading of the assignment, the material should be resubmitted
  to instructor for full reconsideration. Under no circumstances will anyone
  else make changes to the grades. All requests for re-grading are to be made in
  writing according to the procedure outlined below and must be submitted to
  instructor within one week of receiving the feedback. Note that the entire
  assignment will be regraded and this may result in a lower grade. Late
  re-grades will not be accepted and will not be considered at the end of the
  semester.
</p>
<p>
  The written request for a re-grade must be on a separate piece of paper. DO
  NOT ALTER THE ORIGINAL SUBMISSION. The re-grade must include an explanation as
  to why you feel the problem should be re-graded. I will not discuss with you
  whether or not you should submit a re-grade. "Brief comparisons" which consist
  of "I think I deserve more points" or “the answer is correct because my friend
  had the same answer” are NOT reconsidered.
</p>
<p>
  Note: Addition errors made during point totaling are not considered re-grades
  and may be given to the instructor for correction at any time during the
  semester.
</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem111</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 130</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem130</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  This course is a one-semester college level introductory chemistry course
  covering the fundamental principles of general, organic, and biochemistry.
  Three credits, fulfills the General Education (GN) requirements.
</p>
<p>
  Course topics include dimensional analysis, atomic structure and periodicity,
  chemical bonding, molecular structure, states of matter and intermolecular
  forces, basic gas laws, solutions and solubility, acids, bases and
  equilibrium, reaction stoichiometry and thermodynamics. In addition,
  fundamentals of organic nomenclature, properties of main organic functional
  groups, and structure and function of biological macromolecules will be
  discussed. The course will emphasize chemistry in environmental and
  health-related contexts.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>
  The overall objective of this course is for students to gain knowledge of
  fundamental principles in the areas of general chemistry, organic chemistry,
  and biochemistry. Since many of the students enrolled in this course will be
  majoring in environmental or health related sciences, this course will
  emphasize chemistry as it appears in environmental and health related
  contexts. The specific learning objectives are listed below:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>General Learning Objectives: Students will be able to...</li>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Apply scientific reasoning and methods of inquiry to explain chemical
      phenomena.
    </li>
    <li>
      Demonstrate effective problem-solving and critical thinking skills through
      interpreting, analyzing, and evaluating chemical information (both
      qualitative and quantitative).
    </li>
    <li>
      Use their knowledge of general, organic and biochemistry to describe and
      analyze issues in health and environmental sciences.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <li>In the areas of general chemistry, students will be able to...</li>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Perform dimensional analysis to convert between different measurements,
      particularly as applied to health-related situations.
    </li>
    <li>
      Describe the structure of an atom, explain how elements are arranged in
      the periodic table, and understand the periodic trends in atomic
      properties.
    </li>
    <li>
      Name and identify ionic and molecular compounds (either binary or
      containing polyatomic ions), draw Lewis structures of molecular compounds,
      use VSEPR theory to predict molecular shapes, classify whether a molecule
      is polar, and describe the attractive forces in molecular compounds.
    </li>
    <li>
      Apply basic gas laws, especially in regard to the human respiratory
      system.
    </li>
    <li>
      Identify the solute and solvent in a solution, describe the effect of
      temperature, pressure, and intermolecular forces on the solubility,
      identify solutes as electrolytes or nonelectrolytes, and describe how
      solute concentrations affect the properties of a solution.
    </li>
    <li>
      Balance and classify basic chemical reactions, use balanced equations to
      determine relationships between reactants and products, determine the
      limiting reactant, theoretical yield, and percent yield of a reaction.
    </li>
    <li>
      Describe how free energy changes are different for spontaneous and
      non-spontaneous reactions, and explain how variables such as temperature
      and pressure affect the rate of a reaction.
    </li>
    <li>
      Identify common acids and bases, and apply the concepts of pH, acids,
      bases and buffers to problems involving systems of the human body.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <li>In the area of organic chemistry, students will be able to...</li>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Describe how condensed structural formulas and skeletal structures differ.
    </li>
    <li>Classify hydrocarbons as alkanes, alkenes, alkynes, or aromatics</li>
    <li>
      Name and draw the major organic functional groups (alcohols, thiols,
      aldehydes, ketones, acids and acid derivatives, amines, amino acids).
    </li>
    <li>
      Apply the concepts of molecular geometry, polarity, and intermolecular
      forces to describe properties of organic molecules.
    </li>
    <li>
      Describe, draw, and identify constitutional, geometric, and stereoisomers.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <li>In the area of biochemistry, students will be able to...</li>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Identify basic structural elements of carbohydrates, lipids, proteins
      (peptides), and nucleic acids.
    </li>
    <li>
      Understand the structural properties and biological activities of the four
      major groups of biological macromolecules.
    </li>
  </ul>
</ol>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ol>
  <li>
    Textbook: Ball et al,
    <a
      href="https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Introductory_Chemistry/Book%3A_The_Basics_of_GOB_Chemistry_(Ball_et_al.)"
      target="_blank"
      >The basics of General, Organic, and Biological Chemistry</a
    >
    . Publisher: Saylor Academy, 2012, Open (Access) Textbook
  </li>
  <li>
    A suitable non-programmable scientific calculator (one that handles numbers
    in scientific notation and provides log/antilog functions). Calculators with
    text-storage, graphing, or communication capabilities (such as the TI-81
    used in MATH 140, cell-phone calculators, etc) will not be permitted for use
    on CHEM 130 exams.
  </li>
  <li>Webcam</li>
  <li>Photo or Scanning Capabilities (Adobe Scan, CamScanner, etc.)</li>
</ol>
<h2>Midterm / Final Exams</h2>
<p>
  There will be three midterm examinations during the semester and a
  comprehensive final examination during the final exam period. Each exam will
  be administered through a proctoring service called Examity® (more information
  below). Dates and times for midterm exams are flexible; you may sign up to
  take each exam on either Thursday, Friday, or Saturday of each exam week.
</p>
<h2>Make-up Exam</h2>
<p>
  A student having a legitimate excuse for missing any of the three scheduled
  midterms will be provided with a single make-up exam. This cumulative make-up
  exam will cover the material from all three midterms. It is your
  responsibility to obtain permission from your instructor to take this exam.
  The make-up exam will be provided only to students with valid excuses (family
  emergency, illness, university-scheduled activities, etc.).
</p>
<h2>Lectures and Course Content</h2>
<p>
  Most course content is delivered in the form of weekly lessons. Each week you
  will have two lessons to complete (or one lesson on exam weeks). These lessons
  are available on Canvas and consist of a series of lecture videos that are
  accompanied by written lecture notes. After viewing these materials you’ll be
  asked to complete a Knowledge Check Quiz that is based on the lesso
</p>
<p>
  Three versions of the lecture slides are provided with each lesson. “Slides
  without solutions” are lecture slides without any solutions to
  example/practice problems; you’re encouraged to take notes using this version
  of the slides. A copy of the slides with solutions is also provided. The third
  version of the lecture slides contains written notes below each slide
  explaining the content from that slide.
</p>
<h2>Knowledge Check Quizzes</h2>
<p>
  After finishing each lesson you’ll be asked to complete a Knowledge Check
  Quiz. You’ll receive three attempts on each quiz, and only your highest score
  will count. The quiz questions will change from one attempt to the next.
  You’re encouraged to ask for help if you have questions about the quiz
  questions; posting your questions on Piazza is encouraged
</p>
<p>
  Knowledge Check Quizzes are due on Sunday of each week. Knowledge Check
  Quizzes will open two weeks before they are due. The Knowledge Check Quizzes
  account for 13% of the total course grade. At the end of the semester your two
  lowest Knowledge Check scores will be dropped.
</p>
<h2>Homework Assignments</h2>
<p>
  Homework is designed to help you develop basic skills and understand and apply
  your understanding of concepts presented in class. Doing all assigned problems
  is essential to success in this course. Homework assignments can be accessed
  from the Canvas page. You’re encouraged to work with your peers on homework
  assignments, and you’re welcome to ask for help on Piazza, but your submitted
  work must be your own. Homework is due at 11:59pm each Wednesday and should be
  submitted on our Canvas page as a scanned PDF or DOCX file. There are no
  homework assignments in the weeks following exams.
</p>
<p>
  Each homework assignment is scored out of 10 possible points (not equivalent
  to course points). On some occasions homework will be graded solely based on
  completion and effort. On other occasions, however, one randomly selected
  problem from the homework assignment will be graded for 5 points based on
  correctness. On those occasions, completing the rest of the homework
  assignment is worth an additional 5 points, graded based on completeness and
  effort.
</p>
<p>
  The homework scores will be totaled twice during the semester (after exam 2
  and at the end of the semester). You must earn at least 75% of the available
  homework points during each period to earn full course points for that period.
  No extra credit results from accumulating more than 75% of the points during
  that period. There will be no make-up opportunities for homework due to the
  built-in excess of points.
</p>
<p>
  All homework assignments will be submitted electronically using the
  appropriate Canvas page. In order to upload your work you’ll need to either
  scan it or take a high quality photograph of it (we suggest taking a photo
  with a phone). You may be asked to resubmit your assignment if the image
  quality of your scanned work is insufficient. You must upload your work as a
  single PDF or DOCX file in order for Canvas to accept it. One way to do this
  is to use an Android or iOS app that saves photographs on your phone as PDF
  files. You can find many such apps by searching for scanning apps on the
  Google Play Store or Apple App Store. “CamScanner” is a popular app that was
  used by students in previous semesters. Alternatively, you can copy and paste
  an image of your homework into a Microsoft Word document and save it as a DOCX
  file.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<table>
  <th>Assignments</th>
  <th>% of Course Grade</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Exam 1</td>
    <td>15%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Exam 2</td>
    <td>15%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Exam 3</td>
    <td>15%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Final Exam</td>
    <td>25%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Knowledge Check Quizzes</td>
    <td>13%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Homework</td>
    <td>11%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Piazza Participation</td>
    <td>6%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Total</td>
    <td>100%</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>92-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>89-92%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>86-89%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>82-86%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>79-82%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>76-79%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>68-76%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>56-68%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>< 56%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem130</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 202</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem202</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  CHEM 202 is a one-semester, comprehensive course that introduces the students
  to the fundamental principles of organic chemistry including relationships
  between the molecular structure of organic compounds and their macroscopic
  properties. Some of the principles are illustrated with a variety of examples
  from nature and everyday life. The course covers the following topics:
  alkanes; alkenes, including polymers; alkynes; benzene and aromaticity;
  alcohols and phenols; ethers; aldehydes; ketones; carboxylic acids and their
  acyl derivatives; amines; alkyl halides; nomenclature; stereochemistry,
  including conformational analysis and chirality. Chemical reactions of the
  functional groups will be discussed along with the mechanistic details,
  including stereospecificity, of some of these processes. Biological molecules
  such as carbohydrates, lipids, steroids, peptides/proteins and nucleic acids,
  along with their importance in living systems, will be surveyed.
</p>
<p>
  To achieve these goals, we will study the structure and function of organic
  molecules with emphasis on their physical properties and chemical
  reactivities. An understanding of the structure and function of various
  functional groups is essential to master the content of this course.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>When you successfully complete this course, you will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Draw chemical structures for any given chemical formula and be able to name
    the molecules based on IUPAC nomenclature rules.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify and draw constitutional and conformational structural isomers for a
    given formula or structure, including stereoisomers and geometric isomers
    and understand the relationship between them.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe bonding- ionic, covalent, hydrogen bonding and van der Waals
    bonding and understand the concept of hybridization leading to single and
    multiple covalent bonding.
  </li>
  <li>
    Differentiate between bonding, non-bonded interactions and inductive effects
    in the determination of physical properties such as bond polarity, boiling
    points and solubility.
  </li>
  <li>
    Name all classes of molecules. Nomenclature of alkanes, alkenes, alkyl
    halides, aromatic compounds, alcohols, ethers, aldehydes, ketones,
    carboxylic acids and derivatives of carboxylic acids is important.
  </li>
  <li>
    Write chemical reactions and know chemical reagents, reactants and products
    for reactions of alkanes, alkyl halides, alcohols, ethers, aromatic
    compounds, aldehydes, ketones, amines, carboxylic acids and derivatives.
  </li>
  <li>
    Write stepwise reaction mechanisms for nucleophilic substitution reactions
    (SN1 and SN2), elimination reactions (E1 and E2), electrophilic aromatic
    substitutions, nlectrophilic acyl substitution reactions and addition
    reactions, including polymerizations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify enantiomers and diastereomers (meso), optically activity, racemes;
    E/Z geometrical isomers for unsaturated compounds.
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    Fundamentals of Organic Chemistry, by John McMurry, and Eric Simanek. 7th
    edition. Thomson Brooks/Cole. Date published 2011. ISBN-13: 9781439049716.
  </li>
  <li>
    Fundamentals of Organic Chemistry Study Guide and Solutions Manual, by
    McMurry, Susan. 7th edition. Illustrated. Some students find this
    useful.Thomson Brooks/Cole. Date published: 2011. ISBN-13: 9781439049723.
    (optional)
  </li>
  <li>
    Models: A molecular model set is often useful. Recommended Set - Molecular
    Model Set A for Organic Chemistry [Allyn & Bacon (Prenctice Hall)]. ISBN:
    9780205081363. (optional)
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Structure and Bonding</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>Functional Groups and Conformations</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Alkene Structure, Isomerism & Reactions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Additions to Alkenes, Reaction Mechanism</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Aromatic Compounds, Aromaticity, Reactions & Mechanisms</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>
      Stereochemistry, Chirality-enatiomers, Diastereomers, and Meso compounds
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>
      Alkyl Halides
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>
      Midterm Exam
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>
      Alcohols, Phenols, Ethers
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>
      Aldehydes and Ketones
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>
      Carboxylic Acid and Derivatives
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>
      Amines
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>
      Carbohydrate Structure and Function
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>
      Amino acids, Peptides, Proteins. Lipids and Nucleic acids
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>
      Final Exam
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Lesson Structure</h2>
<p>
  Each Lesson contains narrated introductory slides (the PowerPoint slides have
  an audio component), a quiz, and slides from Office Hours.
</p>
<h2>
  Non-proctored, Non-timed Quiz Assignments (220 points)
</h2>
<p>(13 x 20 points each / Drop the two lowest / 60 minutes per attempt)</p>
<p>
  Each lesson will conclude with a quiz which is based on the learning goals
  listed at the end of the Narrated Introductory Slides. If you know how to
  solve the homework problems, you will be able to solve a set of the homework
  problems assigned as a quiz. The best 11 quiz grades will be count. Quiz
  assignments will not be proctored and have to be completed by the due date and
  time. It will be open for one week. A Blackboard Collaborate session will be
  held weekly to discuss the solutions to the quiz questions.
</p>
<h2>Proctored, Timed Midterm Exam (150 points)</h2>
<p>
  On materials learned in Lesson 1 - 7
</p>
<p>
  Students will complete an online, multiple-choice exam consisting of questions
  that will be similar in scope to those given in the quiz assignments. Students
  are NOT allowed to refer to the lessons, the textbook, or their notes to
  complete the exam. Students are not allowed to consult with another person
  while working on the exam. Canvas allows a limited amount of time to complete
  the exam and students are requested to complete the exam within the time
  allotted.
</p>
<h2>Proctored, Timed, Comprehensive, Final Exam (200 points)</h2>
<p>
  Students will complete an online, multiple-choice exam consisting of questions
  that will be similar in scope to those given in the homework assignments. This
  exam will be proctored, and students are not allowed to refer to the lessons,
  the textbook, or their notes to complete the exam. Students are not allowed to
  consult with another person while working on the exam. Canvas allows a limited
  amount of time to complete the exam and students are requested to complete the
  exam within the time allotted.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<table>
  <th>Assignment</th>
  <th>Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Midterm</td>
    <td>150</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Quizzes (13 at 20 points each, lowest 2 scores dropped)</td>
    <td>220</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Final Exam</td>
    <td>200</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Total</td>
    <td>570</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>92-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>90-91%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>88-89%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>82-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>80-81%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>78-79%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>70-77%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>60-69%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td> < 60%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem202</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 810</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem810</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  CHEM 810 is the first in a sequence of liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry
  (LC-MS) courses designed to fill an industry need to provide high-quality
  instruction in LC theory and application. The course topics include the
  background and history of chromatography; fundamental concepts in
  chromatographic separations; basic instrumentation; column, particle and phase
  chemistry; and basic method development. The course material is designed to
  increase student understanding of both the analytical instrument used in the
  laboratory and the principles underlying the measurements. The course
  specifically caters to the needs of the analytical chemical industry and
  individuals newly hired into introductory sample management/preparation and
  quality assurance/quality control positions within companies using liquid
  chromatographic techniques.
</p>
<p>
  There is no required textbook. The bulk of the course uses algebra to solve
  sets of equations. You should feel comfortable doing this and capable of doing
  this in a timely manner. You will also use Microsoft Excel for a number of
  assignments. You should feel comfortable preparing spreadsheets, preparing
  plots, and adding trendlines. If you do not feel confident in these areas talk
  with the instructor early in the semester so you can acquire some proficiency.
  Don’t fall behind. Later material in this course depends strongly on earlier
  material and procrastination can quickly lead to a difficult situation. You
  should set aside regular times during the week for focused study.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>After successfully completing this course, the student will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Identify the factors (and associated equations) which influence the
    efficiency and resolution of a chromatographic separation and be able to
    quantify these contributions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify which factors influence column performance.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify the chemical interactions (intermolecular forces) which give rise
    to analyte separation and use this knowledge to develop isocratic or
    gradient-based elution methods.
  </li>
  <li>
    Evaluate the instrumental contributions (extra-column) to the resolution and
    efficiency of chromatographic separations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify and describe the function of each component of an HPLC system.
  </li>
  <li>
    Design an SPE sample pretreatment method appropriate for the analyte(s) of
    interest.
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Background & History of Chromatography</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>Basics & Terminology</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Introduction to Instrumentation</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Column Basics</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Silica Particles</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>Bonding and Packing</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Intermolecular Forces</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>Stationary Phase Chemistry</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>Mobile Phase Chemistry</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>Basic Method Development</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>Sample Preparation</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Discussions</h2>
<p>
  The first activity is to engage in a class discussion related to that week’s
  assigned problems – questions concerning clarification, problem-solving
  strategies, and placing the questions into a broader context (when/how/why
  might such a problem be useful in the practical application of LC). You must
  post an initial response to any one or all assigned problems by 11:59 PM
  Wednesday of each week. You will then respond to at least two of your
  colleagues during the week. You must post your initial response before you are
  able to respond to others. Even though it is due on Wednesday at the latest,
  the earlier you can post your initial response during the week offers everyone
  a greater opportunity to respond to others. As with any academic work,
  procrastination makes the process more difficult in the long run. Responses to
  your peers, along with your answers to the assigned problems, are due no later
  than 11:59 PM Sunday each week.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<p>
  The course website provides numerous example problems with detailed
  instructor-guided solutions and practice problems for which answer keys are
  provided once an initial answer attempt is submitted. No grade is assigned to
  the instructor-guided example problems or the practice problems.
</p>
<p>
  Each week, a set of 5-10 proficiency- and mastery-level questions associated
  with each module will be assigned. Students are encouraged to discuss the
  questions with each other and the instructor (see Course Schedule above) prior
  to submitting their answers. Answer keys are not provided.
</p>
<p>
  There are a total of 4 exams, one at the end of each module. Each exam is
  comprehensive in scope. A minimum score of 70% is required on an end-of-module
  exam before a student is eligible to access the subsequent module (e.g.., a
  score of 70% is required on Exam 1 – the exam at the end of Module 1 – before
  a student is permitted access to the material in Module 2).
</p>
<p>
  In fairness to the instructor who must grade the required course work, and to
  the other students, late work will not be accepted. Think about this. A
  substantial number of late or missing work will affect your grade. Stay caught
  up.
</p>
<table>
  <th>Assignment</th>
  <th>% of Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Discussion Participation</td>
    <td>200</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Problem Assignments</td>
    <td>400</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Lecture Exams</td>
    <td>400</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Total</td>
    <td>1000</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>Points Earned</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>930-1000</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>900-929</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>870-899</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>820-869</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>780-819</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>750-779</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>700-749</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>600-699</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td> < 600</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem810</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 811</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem811</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>CHEM 811 Syllabus Coming Soon!</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem811</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 812</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem812</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>CHEM 812 Syllabus Coming Soon!</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem812</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frnsc 100</title>
      <link>/syllabi/frnsc100</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  Forensic science is the application of scientific principles and practices to
  matters of the law.
</p>
<p>
  This course introduces students to the field of forensic science and
  criminalist with focus on the collection, examination, evaluation, and
  interpretation of evidence. Following a single case over the semester, the
  course will review the basic applications of selected forensic science
  disciplines and will explore the underlying scientific principals and methods
  used within each. The capabilities and limitations of the forensic sciences
  will be illustrated, as well as the ways in which science contributes to the
  resolution of social and legal disputes.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>Upon completion of this course, students will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Describe crime scene procedures and technologies used to reveal, collect,
    process, and transport crime scene evidence.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify the role of the criminalist within the broad scope of forensic
    science and science in general.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the forensic roles that scientists from the fields outside of
    criminalistics play in the investigation and criminal justice process.
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain categories of evidence (direct, circumstantial, testimonial), their
    limitations, and value in a criminal investigation.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the necessity of photography in all stages of the forensic science
    process, from crime scene to court room, and its dual purpose as both
    evidence and documentation in case work.
  </li>
  <li>
    Compare the generalist versus specialist philosophies of forensic science,
    and explain how each informs the way forensic science is approached.
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain how to identify and scientifically examine different types of
    physical evidence, such as glass, soil, hairs, fibers, paint, controlled
    substances or drugs, blood, DNA, etc.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe identification, enhancement, collection, and analysis techniques
    for impression and pattern evidence.
  </li>
  <li>
    List characteristics of handwriting and document analysis.
  </li>
  <li>
    Recall historical developments and landmarks of forensic science.
  </li>
  <li>
    Illustrate critical thinking by obtaining results and collecting facts, and
    then drawing conclusions from those results and making decisions based on
    the facts presented.
  </li>
  <li>
    Demonstrate knowledge of the underlying scientific principles for analyses
    performed and instruments used in forensic science and the science lab.
  </li>
  <li>
    Demonstrate quantitative literacy by solving numerical problems and
    performing numerical manipulations, and interpreting tabulated, graphical,
    and/or statistical data.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify the limitations of forensic science in what it can and cannot
    prove.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the differences between presumptive and confirmatory testing, and
    demonstrate knowledge of the appropriate application of each to evidence.
  </li>
  <li>
    Relate forensic science principles and technological advances to real-world
    applications.
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain the importance of ethics in science.
  </li>
  <li>
    Summarize how the legal field influences forensic science and vise-versa.
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the role of forensic science in the criminal justice system, as
    well as its role in society at large.
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    Houde, J. N. (2006). Crime Lab: A Guide for Nonscientists (Second ed.).
  </li>
  <li>Rollingbay, WA: Calico Press, LLC. ISBN: 978-0965828666</li>
</ul>
<p>
  It is HIGHLY recommended that you purchase the e-book. You can buy it on
  amazon.com. You do not need a kindle to read the book - just download the free
  kindle app onto your computer or device.
</p>
<p>
  The Kindle version costs approx. $6 USD and can be purchased on
  <a
    href="https://www.amazon.com/Crime-Lab-Guide-Nonscientists-2nd-ebook/dp/B01CTHYAZ2/ref=sr_1_1_twi_kin_1?ie=UTF8&qid=1502221118&sr=8-1&keywords=crime+lab+a+guide+for+nonscientists%20(Links%20to%20an%20external%20site.)Links%20to%20an%20external%20site."
    target="_blank"
    >Amazon</a
  >
  .
</p>
<p>
  If you choose to buy the paper book instead of the e-book, no dude date
  extensions will be granted for late work because your book has has not arrived
  yet. The paper book costs about $30 USD, so it is remarkably more expensive
  than the e-book. If you still decide to purchase the physical copy, make sure
  you purchase the second edition and not the first. They are not the same. All
  online instructor provided reading and activities on the Canvas website,
  unless specifically stated to the contrary, are testable materials.
</p>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>
      What is forensic science; crime scene investigation – scene management and
      approach
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>
      Crime scene investigation – processing the scene, evidence collection
      methods
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>
      Crime scene investigation – packaging and transport of evidence
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>
      Forensic biology/serology; collecting evidence samples from
      victims/suspects∏
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>
      Evidence intake and initial examination at crime lab
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>
      Lab instrumentation
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>
      Trace evidence
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>
      Blood
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>
      DNA
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>
      Drug chemistry and toxicology
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>
      Impression evidence; tool marks and firearms
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>
      The courtroom, ethics, and credibility
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>
      Reconstruction and drawing conclusions from results
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>
      Reconstruction and critical thinking
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>
      Forensic science in the “real world;” social/legal impacts
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Reading</h2>
<p>
  Each module contains assigned reading. Some of the reading is from your
  textbook and some will be from online articles, websites, or content provided
  by the instructor on the course content website. All material from the reading
  is testable unless otherwise indicated.
</p>
<p>
  If you have a paper book, the page numbers are listed. If you are using an
  e-book (recommended), the page numbers may differ from the physical paper
  book. In that case, the chapter titles and/or headings are given to provide
  you with starting and stopping points.
</p>
<h2>Online Labs or Activities</h2>
<p>
  Online labs or other activities help emphasize important points from your
  reading, or help expand your understanding of the science being used to
  examine evidence. Most of this content is hosted on third-party websites that
  we do not control. If the content on one of these websites becomes unavailable
  or you have trouble accessing it, email the instructor immediately for
  assistance. We will help you troubleshoot as best we can. If you choose to
  skip the activity and move on to the quiz without seeking assistance, and are
  unable to answer quiz questions because of it, points will not be given back.
  You MUST contact one of us to troubleshoot before "giving up and moving on" if
  you cannot access a site in order for points to be granted for missed
  questions.
</p>
<p>
  If you do not already have a YouTube account, you may need to create one to
  watch many of the videos.
</p>
<p>
  The content of these labs and activities is testable material unless otherwise
  indicated.
</p>
<h2>Case Notes and Written Work</h2>
<p>
  In modules 1-11 you will have homework assignments in the form of case notes.
  While each module's case notes covers a different area of the crime scene or
  crime lab (toxicology, DNA, drugs, etc.), they are all part of the same case
  and will all have the same case number – PSUCL-01.
</p>
<p>
  Most of these assignments require you to fill in the provided
  worksheets/outlines and then submit the work for grading on Canvas. All of the
  case notes must be typewritten and submitted as a Microsoft Word or PDF
  document. If you submit your work in a format that is unreadable (bad file,
  .pages, html link, etc.), your work will be given a 0. If we can’t read it, we
  can’t – and won’t - grade it. The same goes for anyone who uses Google Docs.
  If it does funny things to the document format and alters the assignment or
  makes it unreadable, the assignment may lose points or not be graded. YOU are
  responsible for making sure your work is submitted properly and
  legible/readable.
</p>
<p>
  You will need Microsoft Word in order to complete the assignments for this
  class. As a Penn State student, you receive free access to Office 365 online.
  Every single student gets use of the Microsoft Office platforms using this
  app; therefore, no excuses of “But I don’t have Word.” or “But I use a Mac.”
  will be accepted for why your work is not in the proper format. If we cannot
  read it, we cannot grade it.
</p>
<p>
  It is important to keep up with case notes assignments throughout the semester
  - you will need this information to be complete and accurate to do the
  assignments in modules 12-14.
</p>
<h2>Evidence Summary Assignment</h2>
<p>
  In module 12 you will aggregate the results of the case notes that you have
  taken throughout the semester. Your summary will go over each piece of
  evidence by discussing the analyses performed on them and the results of those
  tests.
</p>
<h2>Drawing Conclusions Assignment</h2>
<p>
  In module 13, you will use the summary from module 12. Using your critical
  thinking skills, you will draw conclusions about the evidence in this case. Is
  it probative? Can it be associated with other evidence or people from the
  crime scene? Is your assumption about the evidence supported by science?
</p>
<h2>Timeline of Events (Reconstruction) Assignment</h2>
<p>
  In module 14, you will use the assignment completed in module 13 to
  reconstruct the timeline of events from the crime scene, as well as discuss
  some alternate theories of the case. Based on the conclusions you come to in
  module 13, your timeline may vary greatly from those of your fellow
  classmates. This is expected and acceptable, as long as your timeline is
  backed up by your scientific interpretation of the evidence.
</p>
<h2>Forensic Science Professional Profiles</h2>
<p>
  The majority of the textbook is dedicated to criminalistics, but there are
  many other sciences that can be included under the forensic science umbrella.
  There are ten forensic science specialties discussed throughout the course.
  Each of these will include short reading assignments, a possible online
  activity or lab, and a 5 question, 5 point quiz.
</p>
<h2>Forensic Science Career Assignment</h2>
<p>
  Part of exploring any profession is understanding what it takes to be a part
  of it. You will examine job postings for crime scene, crime lab, and forensic
  specialty work in order to explore what it takes to enter the forensic science
  field. This is also an opportunity to see how the courses you take and the
  skills you develop in the classroom are directly applicable to your career
  once you leave Penn State.
</p>
<h2>Forensic Science Education Assignment</h2>
<p>
  As you will see from the Career Assignment, the educational requirements for
  jobs in the forensic science field vary widely depending on the type of work
  you want to do. For the Education Assignment, you will examine different
  degree options in relation to the job postings you analyzed during the Career
  Assignment to explore the differences between these degrees and why certain
  degrees may be necessary for some jobs but not others.
</p>
<h2>Photography Assignments</h2>
<p>
  You will have five photography assignments throughout the semester. They will
  each cover different uses and necessities of photography throughout a case
  including the use of photography for crime scene investigation (CSI),
  documentation of victims and suspects, initial evidence examination,
  documentation of evidence analysis, and finally the use of these photos as
  evidence or documentation in the courtroom.
</p>
<h2>Quizzes</h2>
<p>
  Each module has a 10 question, 10 point quiz that you will have 10 minutes to
  complete. The quizzes contain multiple choice and true/false questions. All
  material in the module - except for the professional profile - is fair game
  for the quiz.
</p>
<p>
  Quiz questions are randomly drawn from a question bank specific to the module
  in which you are taking the quiz. Each bank may have up to 50 questions. The
  questions are pulled from the textbook reading, Canvas page reading, articles
  and third party website information, videos, and online labs/activities. While
  the quiz is open book, it is HIGHLY RECOMMENDED that you take some notes to
  use on your quiz and exams as you complete each module. Students who try to do
  the reading and take the quiz simultaneously generally run out of time because
  there is not enough time to do both.
</p>
<p>
  Each professional profile has a 5 question, 5 point quiz that you will have 10
  minutes to complete. The quizzes contain multiple choice and true/false
  questions. These quiz questions will only be on the information in the
  professional profile - no other content from the module will be in the 5 point
  quiz.
</p>
<p>
  Quizzes are open book and open note - they are not open friend. Make sure your
  work is your own.
</p>
<p>
  All quizzes will be available on Canvas. Check the calendar and module pages
  for due dates.
</p>
<h2>Case Note Quiz</h2>
<p>
  The formatting of case notes in forensic science is guided by some very strict
  standards and guidelines. In the world of forensic science, case notes are
  considered a legal document, and if they are done incorrectly, they can get
  thrown out of court. You will be introduced to the basics of proper case notes
  documentation in this class. The format you are being asked to follow is a
  bare bones version of what anyone entering a law enforcement or forensics
  profession will encounter. This is also a good introduction to the handwritten
  version of case notes you will encounter in FRNSC 210 if you intend to pursue
  the forensic science major at Penn State.
</p>
<p>
  Every semester, students needlessly lose points on their case notes
  assignments because they refuse to follow the format (or simply ignore the
  directions). This quiz is designed to make sure you understand the format that
  is required for case notes - especially the date and time.
</p>
<h2>Exams</h2>
<p>
  You will have three exams, each worth 100 points. Exams have 100 multiple
  choice and true/false questions. The questions are drawn from the question
  banks used to make the module quizzes. It is likely you will see some of the
  same questions on your exam that you had on a previous quiz - these will be
  mixed in with new questions you have not seen before.
</p>
<p>
  You will have 1 hour (60 minutes) to complete each exam. While the exams are
  open book, it is HIGHLY RECOMMENDED that you take some notes to use on your
  exams as you complete each module. It is also HIGHLY RECOMMENDED that you
  study for this exam the same as you would any other. If you are unfamiliar
  with the material, you will have trouble finishing the exam on time - there is
  not enough time to look up every single answer in your notes or on Canvas
  while taking the exam.
</p>
<h2>Extra Credit</h2>
<p>
  The instructor will have VoiceThread or Kaltura lectures throughout the
  modules for you to watch. A VoiceThread or Kaltura lecture is like a
  PowerPoint lecture - you watch the slides while I talk over them. However,
  these are NOT traditional lectures. They will vary in length and complexity
  depending on the subject matter being discussed and there is not a lecture for
  every module. These lectures are designed to help explain concepts and
  assignments that students have struggled with in the past. It is worth your
  while to watch them with your full attention - do not do other work, watch
  Netflix, or engage in other distractions. Lectures are considered testable
  material unless otherwise stated.
</p>
<h2>Class Discussion on Piazza</h2>
<p>
  There are no discussion boards or group projects required in this class. That
  being said, students in previous classes have expressed a desire for there to
  be some sort of voluntary discussion forum where they can post questions or
  discuss assignments with fellow students. I have set up Piazza so that you can
  do just that. These forums will be monitored, so do not use them to cheat.
  Pointing a student to the correct section of the textbook to find and answer
  is acceptable – telling them the answer is not. This is the ONLY place where
  students are authorized to “collaborate” within this course.
</p>
<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Grade</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>93-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>90-93%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>83-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>83-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>80-83%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>77-80%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>70-77%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>60-70%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>< 60%</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Late Submission Policy</h2>
<p>
  Late quizzes and exams will not be accepted without prior permission from the
  instructor.
</p>
<p>
  Very late work may be accepted on a case-by-case basis. Students with
  long-term or serious illnesses or experiencing catastrophic life events have
  been granted extensions in the past. Doctor's notes or other documentation may
  be required. Again, extensions are not guaranteed, and are granted on a
  case-by-case basis by the instructor.
</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/frnsc100</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 101</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem101</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  CHEM 101 is an introductory chemistry course that incorporates lectures,
  readings, problem-solving and laboratory experiments in developing an
  understanding of chemical concepts and practices. Prior study of chemistry is
  not assumed, but you should have taken at least one class in algebra before
  taking CHEM 101. For some students, CHEM 101 provides the chemistry required
  by their major area of study. For other students, CHEM 101 provides review and
  preparation for subsequent Chemistry classes such as CHEM 110 (Chemical
  Principles I) and CHEM 202 (Fundamentals of Organic Chemistry).
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>When you successfully complete this course, you will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Describe the structure and behavior of atoms</li>
  <li>Extract data and information from the periodic table of the elements</li>
  <li>
    Predict the properties and behavior of elements based on their position in
    the periodic table
  </li>
  <li>
    Understand the process of chemical bonding and predict what type of bonds
    will form between different substances
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine when chemical reactions will take place between substances, the
    ratio in which the substances will combine, what new products will be formed
    in the reaction, and the amount of product formed from a given amount of
    starting materials
  </li>
  <li>
    Correctly name chemical substances based on the ratio of the elements in the
    compound and the type of bonding between the atoms
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify the intramolecular forces that can exist between atoms within a
    chemical compound or molecule and the intermolecular forces that occur
    between molecules
  </li>
  <li>Describe and compare the properties of gases, liquids and solids</li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ol>
  <li>
    Textbook: Introductory Chemistry: A Foundation by Steven Zumdahl and Donald
    Decoste, 7th Edition, 2011, Houghton Mifflin Company publishers. ISBN:
    978-0538736398
  </li>
  <li>CHEM 101 General Tool Kit and CHEM 101 Lab Kit</li>
  <li>
    A suitable scientific calculator (with scientific notation and log
    functions) is essential. Calculators with text-storage capabilities will not
    be permitted for use on exams. Note that MBS is not carrying this for the
    course.
  </li>
</ol>
<h2>Additional Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Isopropyl alcohol (rubbing alcohol) 50%, 70%, or 91%</li>
  <li>Clear white vinegar</li>
  <li>Granulated sugar</li>
  <li>Salt</li>
  <li>Bottled or distilled water</li>
  <li>
    A ruler that is at least 6" in length. Must be marked in cm's with at least
    10 divisions in between the cm's
  </li>
  <li>Measuring spoon set</li>
  <li>Scissors</li>
  <li>Stapler and staples</li>
  <li>Matches</li>
  <li>2 regular ceramic mugs</li>
  <li>1 clear plastic or glass container</li>
  <li>A heat resistant plate</li>
  <li>Disposable plastic teaspoon</li>
  <li>Cotton swabs similar to Q-tips</li>
  <li>Toothpicks</li>
  <li>Paper Towels</li>
  <li>Pen and Pencil</li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Orientation</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>Measurements and Calculations</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Matter</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Chemical Foundations: Electrons, Atoms, Ions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Modern Atomic Theory</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>Chemical Bonding</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Midterm 1 / Nomenclature</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>Chemical Composition</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>Chemical Equations</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>Reactions and Aqueous Solutions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>Classifiying Chemical Reactions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>Midterm 2</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>Chemical Quantities</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>Final Exam</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Lesson Assignments (20%)</h2>
<p>
  Each lesson will conclude with a few homework assignments. The format of each
  assignment will vary and may include fill-in-the blank, short essay, and
  multiple choice questions. Each assignment will be due at the end of each
  lesson before beginning the next lesson. The lowest assignment grade will be
  dropped, and all of the others will be weighted equally.
</p>
<h2>Video Demonstration Summaries (5%)</h2>
<p>
  There will be multiple video demonstrations for some of the lessons. A short
  online submission (one page or less in length) will be required for five of
  the demonstrations. Each submission will go into a separate dropbox and must
  include a description of the demonstration, the concept being presented, your
  observations, and any suggestions you may have to change or expand the
  demonstration. Watch all the videos, but please only submit summaries for 5 of
  the videos.
</p>
<h2>Lab Experiment Reports (25%)</h2>
<p>
  There will be four lab experiments performed individually by the student. Each
  experiment will have an online report submitted consisting of experimental
  data, observations and short answers to interpretive questions.
</p>
<h2>Non-Proctored Online Mid-Term Exams (30%)</h2>
<p>
  The two exams will have multiple choice questions. Both will have a 90-minute
  time limit. Only one attempt is allowed. Each exam will be worth 15% of the
  final grade.
</p>
<h2>Non-Proctored, Closed-Book, Comprehensive Final Exam (20%)</h2>
<p>
  Students will complete a closed-book final exam consisting of multiple-choice
  questions that will be similar in scope to those given in the homework
  assignments and mid-term exams. Students will need to print out the Useful
  Information file located in the Exams folder, which may be used when
  completing the final exam. The file includes a periodic table, a list of key
  equations, and a solubility table.
</p>
<p>
  You will also need a scientific calculator to take the Final Exam. If you want
  to know whether your calculator is allowed, email your instructor as soon as
  possible.
</p>
<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>91.5-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>89.5-91.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>85.5-89.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>78.5-80.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>74.5-78.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>68.5-74.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>56.5-68.4%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>< 56.4%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem101</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frnsc 200</title>
      <link>/syllabi/frnsc200</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  This course offers an exploration of the science, management, and
  investigative techniques for the field of crime scene investigation. Students
  will develop the intellectual skills needed to be able to plan for and
  organize a crime scene investigation. Each student will understand the nature
  and value of each kind of physical evidence and how to recognize, collect and
  preserve it. They will research all the topics in this course and provide
  their own evidence of competency in each in the form of a professional
  portfolio.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>When you successfully complete this course, you will understand:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Techniques used to preserve the crime scene record (notes, sketches, and
    digital SLR photography).
  </li>
  <li>
    Techniques used to recognize, enhance, document, collect, handle, and
    package physical evidence. Comprehension of importance of chain of custody
    and evidence integrity.
  </li>
  <li>
    Common field tests for the presumptive identification and enhancement of
    different types of physical evidence.
  </li>
  <li>
    Incident/crime reconstruction including the analysis of blood traces and
    projectile trajectory analysis.
  </li>
  <li>
    Proper preparation and maintenance of case folders.
  </li>
  <li>
    Techniques to communicate results including verbal and written
    communication.
  </li>
  <li>
    Scene management techniques including allocation of personnel, resources,
    and time.
  </li>
  <li>
    Importance of science and scientific, objective, critical thought processes
    in scene investigations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Role and impact of the criminalist in incident scene investigations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Codes of professional conduct and ethics for forensic science professional
    organizations; comprehension of necessity of ethics in forensic science and
    potential ethical problems in forensic science including issues of
    professional practice, technical competence, and bias.
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Introduction to the Course; CSI; Forensics; Ethics</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>Scene Management; CSI Team Structure; Evidence Collection</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Documentation: Motes, Sketches, Scene Entry Logs, Other Forms</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Photography I (general photography)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Photography II (CSI photography; photographing people)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>Fingerprints</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Pattern Evidence</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>Trace Evidence</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>Biological Evidence; Sexual Assault</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>Firearms</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>Fires; Explosions; Mass Fatalities</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>Digital Evidence; Questioned Documents</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>Autopsy; Entomology; Drugs</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>Analysis of Blood Traces</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>Aspects of Shooting Incident Investigation I</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>16</td>
    <td>Aspects of Shooting Incident Investigation II</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grading</h2>
<table>
  <th>Assignment</th>
  <th>Assignment Weight</th>
  <th>Final Weight</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Exercises (6)</td>
    <td>3.75%</td>
    <td>22.50%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Final Mock Scene Exercise</td>
    <td>9.50%</td>
    <td>9.50%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Quiz (6)</td>
    <td>5%</td>
    <td>30%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Midterm Exam</td>
    <td>12%</td>
    <td>24%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Final Exam</td>
    <td>14%</td>
    <td>14%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% of Course Grade</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>93-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>A-</td>
    <td>90-93%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B+</td>
    <td>83-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>83-87%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B-</td>
    <td>80-83%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C+</td>
    <td>77-80%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>70-77%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>60-70%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>< 60%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/frnsc200</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frnsc 210</title>
      <link>/syllabi/frnsc210</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  The primary aim of this course is to prepare students for entry into the
  undergraduate forensic science program and to enhance success in the 400 level
  forensic science courses. This course is designed to introduce students to
  several fundamental areas and provide the theory and knowledge essential for
  success in the ﬁeld. The associated skills and abilities for these practices
  will be developed in later courses required for the forensic science program.
</p>
<p>
  Presently, forensic science and criminalistics are primarily specialized;
  forensic biologists, forensic chemists, trace evidence examiners, latent print
  specialists, ﬁrearm and tool mark examiners, etc. While some criminalists may
  be cross-trained in other areas, the majority practice solely in a speciﬁc
  sub-discipline. Regardless of the specialty, all criminalists and forensic
  scientists will be exposed to and required to perform many of the same
  essential practices. All criminalists will record observations, in the ﬁeld
  and in the laboratory, as case notes. They will prepare sketches, take and
  record measurements, and photograph scenes and/or physical evidence.
  Microscopes are used in nearly every sub-discipline for the examination of
  physical evidence. Criminalists are expected to report and testify to their
  examinations, analyses, results, and conclusions.
</p>
<p>
  This course is designed to introduce students to these fundamental areas and
  provide the theory and knowledge essential for success in the ﬁeld. The
  associated skills and abilities for these practices will be developed in later
  courses. FRNSC 210 provides a ﬁrm foundation for all later courses; it is the
  cornerstone of your education and will serve you well as a criminalist. This
  knowledge cannot be forgotten upon completion of this course; it must be
  retained as it comprises the essential practices required of all criminalists
  and forensic scientists.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>On completion of FRNSC 210, students will be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Describe Kirk’s philosophy of criminalistics and the importance of
    scientific philosophy in forensic science
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe accuracy, precision, uncertainty of measurement, and assessment of
    error
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the terms and organizations: quality assurance; quality control;
    accreditation; proficiency testing; ASCLD; and ASCLD-LAB.
  </li>
  <li>
    Demonstrate the required ISO/17025 and ASCLD-LAB criteria for note taking at
    a crime scene or in the laboratory
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain the proper preparation and maintenance of case folders
  </li>
  <li>
    Execute techniques used to preserve the crime scene record, e.g., to take
    appropriate notes, make proper sketches, and properly use digital SLR
    photography
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the importance of evidence integrity and chain of custody as well
    as demonstrate its use
  </li>
  <li>
    Perform various measurement methods used at crime scenes and evidence
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain the use of f/stop, shutter speed, and ISO in capturing a properly
    exposed image
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe color temperature and how it affects a captured image and the
    apparent color of an object
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain proper exposures for different lighting conditions
  </li>
  <li>
    Explain resolution and magnification in visible light images including
    calculating focal length
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe various aberrations of lenses and their corrections
  </li>
  <li>
    List different microscopes and their uses in a crime lab including
    advantages and limitations
  </li>
  <li>
    Employ techniques to communicate data, results, and interpretations through
    written communication
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<p>
  Langford M, Bilissi E. Langford’s Advanced Photography. 8th ed. Oxford: Focal
  Press, 2011.
</p>
<p>Additional assigned reading materials will be provided by the instructor.</p>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>
      Introduction<br />National Academy of Science Report on Forensic Science
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>
      Forensic science, criminalistics, science, and evidence<br />Professional
      Organizations in Forensic Science
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>
      Quality Assurance, Quality Control and Accreditation<br />Physical
      evidence: control and authentication
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>
      Observations and Preservation of physical evidence record: Notes and
      sketches
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>
      Measurement: tools, techniques, and accuracy/error
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>
      Introduction to Light and Photography I
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>
      Introduction to Optics and Photography II
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>
      Photography III: Cameras, Lenses, and Lighting
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>
      Videography
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>
      Forensic Microscopy I
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>
      Forensic Microscopy II: Phase Contrast and Darkfield
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>
      Forensic Microscopy III: Polarized Light and Fluorescence
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>
      Forensic Microscopy IV
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>
      Thanksgiving Break
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>
      Communication of Results I
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>16</td>
    <td>
      Communication of Results II
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grading</h2>
<table>
  <th>Assignment</th>
  <th>Points (each)</th>
  <th>% of Total Grade</th>
  <tr>
    <td>Midterm Exam</td>
    <td>100</td>
    <td>20%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Final Exam</td>
    <td>150</td>
    <td>30%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Quizzes (5)</td>
    <td>20(each) 100(total)</td>
    <td>20%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Exercises (3)</td>
    <td>50(each) 150(total)</td>
    <td>10%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Total</td>
    <td>500</td>
    <td>100%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/frnsc210</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Math 004</title>
      <link>/syllabi/math004</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  MATH 004 Intermediate Algebra (3 semester hours) Algebraic expressions;
  linear, absolute value Equations and inequalities; lines; systems of linear
  equations; integral exponents; polynomials; factoring. This course may not be
  used to satisfy the basic minimum requirements for graduation in any
  Baccalaureate degree program.
</p>
<h2>Prerequisite</h2>
<p>
  Basic arithmetic skills or satisfactory performance on the mathematics
  proficiency examination, Students who do not meet the prerequisite may have
  great difficulty in the course.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Unit 1</li>
  <ul>
    <li>Simplify numerical expressions.</li>
    <li>Perform arithmetic operations with real numbers.</li>
    <li>Apply properties of real numbers to simplify expressions.</li>
    <li>Evaluate exponential expressions.</li>
    <li>Simplify and evaluate algebraic expressions.</li>
  </ul>
  <li>Unit 2</li>
  <ul>
    <li>Solve first-degree equations.</li>
    <li>Use equations to solve word problems.</li>
    <li>Solve equations involving fractions or decimals.</li>
    <li>
      Solve word problems involving discount and. selling price, simple
      interest, and mixtures.
    </li>
    <li>Solve inequalities, and write solution sets in interval notation.</li>
    <li>Solve inequalities involving fractions or decimals.</li>
    <li>Solve compound inequalities.</li>
    <li>Use inequalities to solve word problems.</li>
    <li>Solve equations and inequalities that involve absolute value.</li>
  </ul>
  <li>Unit 3</li>
  <ul>
    <li>Determine the slope of a line, and use slope to graph lines.</li>
    <li>Determine the point-slope equation of a line.</li>
    <li>Determine the slope-intercept equation of a line.</li>
    <li>Find equations for parallel or perpendicular lines.</li>
    <li>Find and graph solutions for linear equations in two variables.</li>
    <li>Graph linear equations by finding the x and y intercept.</li>
    <li>
      Graph lines passing through the origin, vertical lines, and horizontal
      lines.
    </li>
    <li>Use the distance formula.</li>
    <li>Solve systems of linear equations by graphing and substitution.</li>
  </ul>
  <li>Unit 4</li>
  <ul>
    <li>Add, subtract, and multiply polynomials.</li>
    <li>Divide monomials.</li>
    <li>Factor out the greatest common factor.</li>
    <li>Factor by grouping.</li>
    <li>
      Factor the difference of two squares and the sum or difference of two
      cubes.
    </li>
    <li>Factor trinomials by trial-and-error and the four-step method.</li>
    <li>Solve polynomial equations by factoring.</li>
  </ul>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    An 18 week Access to ALEKS 360 is needed to provide access to the ebook and
    supplementary materials
    <a href="https://www.aleks.com/" target="_blank">www.aleks.com</a>
    . This can be purchased separately or with the book.
  </li>
  <li>ALEKS Course Code : MNPMR-LFYMA</li>
</ul>
<h2>Textbook</h2>
  <p>Intermediate Algebra with P.O.W.E.R Learning 1st edition, Messersmith, Perez, Feldman </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Ebook with 1 semester ALEKS 360 access (18 weeks) ISBN-10: 0077528530</li>
    <li>Paperback (ALEKS access not included) ISBN-10: 0073406279</li>
  </ul>
</ul>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<table>
  <th>Conceptual</th>
  <th>Basic Skills</th>
  <th>Exams</th>
  <tr>
    <td>200 Points</td>
    <td>350 Points</td>
    <td>450 Points</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4 Piazza Participations (25 points each)</td>
    <td>4 Scheduled ALEKS Assessments (20 each)</td>
    <td>Final Exam Proctored (250 points)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4 Concept Quizzes (25 points each) </td>
    <td>4 Unit ALEKS Quizzes (20 each)</td>
    <td>Midterm (200 points) </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td>4 ALEKS Unit Completion (30 each)<br>Midterm and Final ALEKS Units (35 each)</td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
</table>
<h2>Grade Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% Course Grade</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>90-100%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>80-89%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>70-79%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>60-69%</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td> < 59%</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/math004</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Math 017</title>
      <link>/syllabi/math017</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Coming Soon!</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/math017</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Math 021</title>
      <link>/syllabi/math021</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  An extensive look into Quadratic equations; equations in quadratic form; word
  problems, graphing; algebraic fractions; negative and rational exponents, and
  radicals.
</p>
<h2>Prerequisite</h2>
<p>
  Math 4 or satisfactory performance on the mathematics proficiency examination.
  Students who do not meet the prerequisite may have great difficulty in the
  course.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>
  <strong>Unit 0</strong>
  is designed to ascertain prerequisite knowledge and skills which will
  facilitate success in this class. Students are expected to know and/or review
  and master most of these review topics on ALEKS within the first week of the
  class. Some of the topics are reviewed as needed in subsequent units.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Simplify numerical expressions.</li>
  <li>Perform arithmetic operations with real numbers.</li>
  <li>Apply properties of real numbers to simplify expressions.</li>
  <li>Evaluate basic exponential expressions.</li>
  <li>Simplify and evaluate basic algebraic expressions.</li>
  <li>Solve first-degree equations.</li>
  <li>Use equations to solve word problems.</li>
  <li>Solve equations involving fractions or decimals.</li>
  <li>
    Solve basic word problems involving discounts and selling price, simple
    interest, and mixtures.
  </li>
  <li>Solve inequalities, and write solution sets in interval notation.</li>
  <li>Solve inequalities involving fractions or decimals.</li>
  <li>Solve compound inequalities.</li>
  <li>Use inequalities to solve word problems.</li>
  <li>Solve equations and inequalities that involve absolute value.</li>
  <li>Find and graph solutions for linear equations in two variables.</li>
  <li>Graph linear equations by finding the x and y intercepts.</li>
  <li>
    Graph lines passing through the origin, vertical lines, and horizontal
    lines.
  </li>
  <li>Use the distance formula.</li>
  <li>Determine the slope of a line, and use slope to graph lines.</li>
  <li>Determine the point-slope equation of a line.</li>
  <li>Determine the slope-intercept equation of a line.</li>
  <li>Find equations for parallel or perpendicular lines.</li>
  <li>Add, subtract, and multiply polynomials.</li>
  <li>Divide monomials.</li>
  <li>Factor out the greatest common factor.</li>
  <li>Factor by grouping.</li>
  <li>
    Factor the difference of two squares and the sum or difference of two cubes.
  </li>
  <li>Factor trinomials by trial-and-error and the four-step method.</li>
  <li>Solve polynomial equations by factoring.</li>
  <li>Solve systems of linear equations by graphing and substitution</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <strong>Unit 1</strong>
  contains review topics, however some of the topics may extend ideas which may
  be new to students. Upon successfully completing this unit, the student should
  be able to:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Determine and interpret the slope of a line as a rate of change from: a
    table, a set of ordered points, an equation or a graph.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine and utilize the point-slope equation of a line.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine and utilize the slope-intercept equation of a line.
  </li>
  <li>Determine if two given lines are perpendicular or parallel.</li>
  <li>
    Write linear equations and graph lines that are parallel and perpendicular
    to a given line and passing through a given point.
  </li>
  <li>
    Apply The Pythagorean Formula to create and use the distance formula to find
    and interpret the distance between any two points on a line.
  </li>
  <li>Use the midpoint formula.</li>
  <li>
    Identify linear, quadratic, cubic, square root and absolute value functions
    from algebraic, graphical, tabular and verbal representations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Use function notation and piecewise defined function notation when
    evaluating polynomial and absolute value functions respectively.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine the solution set for linear inequalities and graph the solution
    set on a number line.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine the solution set for absolute value equations and inequalities and
    graph the solution set on a number line.
  </li>
  <li>
    Translate applications into algebraic models (equations and inequalities)
    involving linear and absolute value functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine and interpret the solution sets for applications modeled by linear
    and absolute value equations and inequalities.
  </li>
  <li>
    Understand and utilize set notation and interval notation to describe,
    interpret and plot intervals and discrete points on a number line.
  </li>
  <li>
    Solve a system of two linear equations in two variables by substitution,
    graphing or elimination.
  </li>
  <li>
    Solve a system of three linear equations in three variables by elimination.
  </li>
  <li>
    Model applications which may be represented by a system of 2 linear
    equations and determine the solution set of the resulting system.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  <strong>Unit 2</strong>
  consists of topics associated with polynomial and rational expressions and
  functions. Upon successfully completing this unit, the student should be able
  to:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Solve literal equations (solve for one variable in terms of another).</li>
  <li>Factor basic algebraic expressions (GCF and polynomial factoring).</li>
  <li>Simplify rational expressions.</li>
  <li>Add, subtract, multiply, and divide rational expressions.</li>
  <li>Simplify complex fractions.</li>
  <li>
    Identify Polynomial and Rational functions from algebraic, graphical,
    tabular and verbal representations.
  </li>
  <li>Determine the solution set for polynomial and rational equations.</li>
  <li>
    Translate applications into algebraic models involving polynomial and
    rational functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine and interpret the solution sets for applications modeled by
    polynomial and rational functions.
  </li>
  <li>Determine the solution sets of polynomial and rational inequalities.</li>
  <li>
    Identify graphs and develop graphs for basic polynomial and rational
    functions by utilizing symmetry, intercepts, and translation techniques.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  <strong>Unit 3</strong>
  consists of topics associated with radical expressions and functions. Upon
  successfully completing this unit, the student should be able to:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Identify Radical functions from algebraic and graphical representations.
  </li>
  <li>
    Convert from radical notation to rational exponent notation and from
    exponent notation to radical notation.
  </li>
  <li>Simplify radical expressions.</li>
  <li>Add, subtract, multiply, and divide radical expressions.</li>
  <li>Simplify radical expressions in terms of i.</li>
  <li>
    Add, subtract, multiply, and divide complex numbers and write solutions in
    standard form.
  </li>
  <li>Determine and verify solution sets of radical equations.</li>
  <li>
    Translate applications into algebraic models involving radical functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine, verify, and interpret the solution sets for applications modeled
    by radical functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Identify graphs and develop graphs for basic radical functions by plotting
    points and utilizing translation techniques.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  <strong>Unit 4</strong>
  consists of topics associated with quadratic equations and inequalities,
  quadratic models, parabolas, circles and applications of the midpoint and
  distance formulas. Upon successfully completing this unit, the student should
  be able to:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Determine the solution set of quadratic equations by factoring, using the
    square root property, completing the square, and the quadratic formula.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine the number and type of solutions to a quadratic equation using the
    discriminant.
  </li>
  <li>
    Given a quadratic function, write in standard form, identify the vertex and
    whether the vertex represents a maximum or minimum value.
  </li>
  <li>
    Write the quadratic function which represents a given graph of a parabola.
  </li>
  <li>
    Graph parabolas utilizing the vertex, symmetry, intercepts, end-behavior and
    translation techniques.
  </li>
  <li>
    Translate applications into algebraic models involving quadratic functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Determine and interpret the solution sets for applications modeled by
    quadratic functions.
  </li>
  <li>
    Apply the distance formula and the midpoint formula to geometric
    applications.
  </li>
  <li>
    Interpret the description or graph of a circle to identify the center and
    the radius and write the equation of the circle in standard form.
  </li>
  <li>
    Convert a non-standard equation of a circle to standard form by completing
    the square and identify the center and radius.
  </li>
  <li>Graph circles from equations using the center and radius.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<p>
  One-semester subscription access to ALEKS and the electronic copy of
  "Intermediate Algebra, 4th edition" published by McGraw-Hill, 2013. Authors:
  Julie Miller, Molly O'Neill, and Nancy Hyde. Access to ALEKS combined with
  access to the eBook can be purchased through ALEKS (<a
    href="https://www.aleks.com/"
    target="_blank"
    >www.aleks.com</a
  >
  ) using the course code and instructions found in the Orientation materials.
  The price is approximately $85. This option is much less expensive than buying
  the book and the code separately.
</p>
<h2>Textbook (Optional)</h2>
<p>
  If you would like a hard copy of the text, you may purchase the text from an
  online text vendor of your choice. The ISBN is 9780073384498.
</p>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Unit</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>0</td>
    <td>Review and Readiness</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Solving Linear Equations and Linear Systems</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>Polynomial and Rational Expressions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Radical Expressions and Complex Numbers</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Quadratic Equations, Functions, and Inequalities and Circles</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Algebraic Skills</h2>
<p>
  Algebraic skills will be primarily developed through work on ALEKS. ALEKS is a
  web-based tutorial system which provides students with ongoing skills based
  assessments and tracks progress. The midterm and final exams will also entail
  skills based problems.
</p>
<p>
  As necessary, lectures will be done via BlackBoard Collaborate. The midterm
  and final exams will administered via Canvas.
</p>
<h2>ALEKS</h2>
<p>
  Essentially all of the skills based work will be conducted through ALEKS. The
  ALEKS system will do ongoing assessments of skills based problems and track
  student progress. ALEKS is a major component of the course and a typical
  college algebra student will need to plan on 5-8 hours of online work each
  week (60-90 hours for the course). Skills based points will be earned by
  measuring mastered objective milestones and skills based ALEKS quizzes.
</p>
<h2>Canvas</h2>
<p>
  The course management system is Canvas. Canvas will be used to deliver, the
  midterm exam and the final exam and associated practice/study exams.
</p>
<h2>PIAZZA & BlackBoard Collaborate</h2>
<p>
  Participation in the course is gauged via a student's interaction on Piazza
  and live sessions. Students are expected to ask questions, pose problems and
  answer questions via the Piazza bulletin board.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<p>
  The total number of points for the course will be 600 points. Work completed
  in ALEKS, which builds skills, will be worth 230 points. Participation points
  for active participation on the Piazza bulletin board and BlackBoard Live
  sessions is worth 20 points. The last component of the course consists of two
  (2) proctored exams, a midterm exam (150 points) and a comprehensive final
  exam (200 points). The final grade will be determined by the sum of these four
  areas.
</p>
<table>
  <th>PIAZZA & BlackBoard</th>
  <th>ALEKS</th>
  <th>CANVAS Exams</th>
  <tr>
    <td>4 Participation Discussions (5 pts / each)</td>
    <td>Readiness Assessment (10 pts)</td>
    <td>Midterm Exam (150 pts)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td>4 ALEKS Quizzes (40 pts / each)</td>
    <td>Final Exam (200 pts)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td>6 Unit Reviews (10 pts / each)</td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>20 pts</td>
    <td>230 pts</td>
    <td>350 pts</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Grading Scale</h2>
<table>
  <th>Letter Grade</th>
  <th>% Score</th>
  <th>Total Points</th>
  <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>90-100</td>
    <td>537-600</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>80-89</td>
    <td>477-536</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>70-79</td>
    <td>417-476</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>60-69</td>
    <td>357-416</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>0-59</td>
    <td>0-356</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/math021</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Math 022</title>
      <link>/syllabi/math022</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  College Algebra II represents a significant opportunity for students to
  discover the beauty and practical power of mathematics. Concepts and skills
  are taught while at the same time a sense of algebra's utility in the real
  world is imparted. This course provides indepth coverage of college algebra
  topics that students continuing in mathematics will require. This is the kind
  of mathematics that students will use the rest of their lives in many fields.
  MATH 022 is a preparatory course intended to provide mathematical background
  in algebra with a function/graph emphasis required in calculus courses.
  Linear, polynomial, rational, exponential and logarithmic functions and their
  graphs provide necessary models for mathematical applications.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>Upon successful completion fo the course, students should be able to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Solve various types of basic equations.</li>
  <li>Solve linear, absolute value, non-linear and rational inequalities.</li>
  <li>
    Identify functions from algebraic, graphical, tabular and verbal
    representations.
  </li>
  <li>Use function notation when evaluating functions.</li>
  <li>Identify domain and range of functions.</li>
  <li>Graph a piece-wise defined function.</li>
  <li>
    Identify properties of graphs such as relative and global extrema, symmetry,
    increasing, decreasing, even, and odd.
  </li>
  <li>Identify graphs of Basic Functions and their properties.</li>
  <li>Transform the graph of a function.</li>
  <li>Translate the graph of a circle in standard or general form.</li>
  <li>Write the equation of a line.</li>
  <li>Write equations of parallel and perpendicular lines to a given line.</li>
  <li>Extract information from linear and quadratic models.</li>
  <li>Translate applications into algebraic models and solve.</li>
  <li>Perform operations on functions, including composition of functions.</li>
  <li>Identify one-to-one functions.</li>
  <li>
    Identify, analyze and graph the inverse of a function. Find the inverse of a
    given function.
  </li>
  <li>Analyze and graph polynomials functions.</li>
  <li>Divide a polynomial function by another polynomial function.</li>
  <li>Apply the Remainder Theorem and Factor Theorem.</li>
  <li>Graph rational functions.</li>
  <li>Analyze and graph exponential and logarithmic functions.</li>
  <li>Solve exponential equations.</li>
  <li>Solve logarithmic equations.</li>
  <li>Explain what a logarithm is.</li>
  <li>Use logarithm properties to simplify an expression.</li>
  <li>Set up and solve exponential and logarithmic application problems.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Textbook</h2>
<p>
  College Algebra, 2nd Edition by John W. Coburn (McGraw-Hill, 2010)
  pre-packaged with one-semester access to ALEKS
</p>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <th>Unit</th>
      <th>Topic(s)</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>
        Extensive review of intermediate algebra topics. The review will
        include: solving linear equations and inequalities, fundamental concepts
        associated with quadratic equations, solving equations and inequalities
        with absolute values and other miscellaneous equations involving
        rational expressions and radical expressions. An introduction to complex
        number arithmetic is also included.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>
        General concepts associated with relations and functions. Topics such as
        the algebra of functions, function composition and range and domain are
        studied. The graphical representation of linear and quadratic functions
        are also presented. The algebraic and graphical representation of
        circles will also be studied as it pertains to terminology associated
        with relations in general. Basic graphical transformations are
        introduced.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>
        Polynomial and rational functions are studied in detail. In particular,
        ideas associated with zeros of polynomials, end-behavior, and graph
        sketching are discussed. The unit includes synthetic division, the
        remainder theorem, the conjugate root theorem, horizontal and slant
        (oblique) asymptotes, and vertical asymptotes.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>
        Exponential and logarithmic functions are studied in detail. Specific
        skills entail working with the rules of exponents and logarithms and
        solving exponential and logarithmic equations. Concepts associated with
        one-to-one functions and the existence of inverses are also studied.
        Sketching and recognizing the graphical representation of exponential
        and log functions is included.
      </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2>Algebraic Skills</h2>
<p>
  Algebraic skills will be primarily developed through work on ALEKS. ALEKS is a
  web-based tutorial system which provides students with ongoing skills based
  assessments and tracks progress. The midterm and final exams will also entail
  skills based problems.
</p>
<p>
  As necessary, lectures will be done via BlackBoard Collaborate. The midterm
  and final exams will administered via Canvas.
</p>
<h2>Conceptual Skills</h2>
<p>
  Conceptual Skills will be incorporated in lectures, reading, and activities.
  Lectures and activities will be conducted approximately every other week. A
  typical lecture and/or activity will tie skill based ideas together to provide
  a larger overview of the topics. Lectures will be done via Elluminate and
  activities will be based upon discussion board prompts and/or assigned tasks
  from the text. The final exam will also incorporate questions which relate to
  the conceptual tasks.
</p>
<h2>ALEKS</h2>
<p>
  Essentially all of the skills based work will be conducted through ALEKS. The
  ALEKS system will do ongoing assessments of skills based problems and track
  student progress. ALEKS is a major component of the course and a typical
  college algebra student will need to plan on 4-6 hours of online work each
  week (50-60 hours for the course). Skills based points will be earned by
  measuring mastered objective milestones and skills based ALEKS quizzes.
</p>
<h2>Readings / Problems</h2>
<p>
  he text will be primarily used to tie ideas to concepts and skills together.
  This will be done through assigned readings and suggested problems.
  Occasionally, a problem may be selected to emphasize a specific skill that
  ALEKS did not adequately incorporate. Some of the activities will stem from
  the text. Finally, the text will support the ALEKS work in that explanations
  within ALEKS will reference specific areas from the text for further reading.
</p>
<h2>Lecture Attendance</h2>
<p>
  Elluminate is the web-conference utility where the virtual classroom resides.
  This may also be used for more "face-to-face" group correspondence with
  students.
</p>
<h2>Grading</h2>
<p>
  The total number of points for the course will be 1000 points. Students will
  have an opportunity to earn 200 points in each of the following three areas:
  1) Basic Skills (ALEKS work), 2) Conceptual Understanding (Activities and
  quizzes), and 3) the Final Exam (incorporates both basic skills and conceptual
  understanding). The final grade will be determined by the sum of these three
  areas. The minimum of the three area scores and the maximum of the three area
  scores will be incorporated twice and thus each of these two areas will will
  contribute to 40% of your overall grade as each will be worth 400 points. This
  rubric emphasizes that all three areas are of utmost importance.
</p>
<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <th>Conceptual Assessment</th>
      <th>Basic Skills</th>
      <th>Final Exam</th>
      <th>Minimum 3 Areas</th>
      <th>Maximum 3 areas</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4 Activities (5 pts / each)</td>
      <td>4 ALEKS Units (40 pts / each)</td>
      <td>1 Proctored Exam (200 pts)</td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4 Quizzes (20 pts / each)</td>
      <td>Final Set (40 pts)</td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2 Midterm Exams (50 pts / each)</td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>200 pts</td>
      <td>200 pts</td>
      <td>200 pts</td>
      <td>200 pts</td>
      <td>200 pts</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2>Grading Scale</h2>
<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <th>Letter Grade</th>
      <th>% Score</th>
      <th>Total Points</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A</td>
      <td>90-100</td>
      <td>896-1000</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>B</td>
      <td>80-89</td>
      <td>796 -895</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>C</td>
      <td>70-79</td>
      <td>696-795</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>D</td>
      <td>60-69</td>
      <td>596-695</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>F</td>
      <td>0-59</td>
      <td>50-595</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2>Arranging a Proctor</h2>
<p>
  You will need to secure a proctor in order to take exams in this course. A
  proctor will not automatically be assigned to you; rather, you must make the
  necessary contacts to secure a professional who will serve in this capacity.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Contact a person who meets the qualifications and ask him or her to proctor
    your exam.
  </li>
  <li>
    Student Services must approve your proctor before any exams can be taken.
    Please see instructions for securing a
    <a
      href="https://student.worldcampus.psu.edu/courses/proctored-exams"
      target="_blank"
      >suitable proctor</a
    >
    . While many proctors will serve on a voluntary basis, you are responsible
    for paying any expenses incurred in retaining a proctor.
  </li>
  <li>
    You must complete a Proctor Information Form and submit the completed form
    with the proctor verification documentation. Note: If your proctor has been
    previously approved by the World Campus during a prior course within two
    years, you do not need to obtain verification. World Campus retains proctor
    information on file for two years.
  </li>
  <li>
    If your proctor does not meet the required specifications, Student Services
    will notify you within 5 to 7 business days.
  </li>
  <li>
    You will need to complete an Exam Request Form for each exam. Contact your
    proctor to confirm the date, time, and location of your exam(s). Complete
    the form 3 weeks prior to your scheduled exam to allow for processing the
    request and mailing exams to proctors. If you are located outside the United
    States, in order to allow adequate time for mailing, please plan to request
    your exam earlier than 3 weeks prior to the exam week.
  </li>
  <li>Contact Student Services if you cannot take a scheduled exam.</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/math022</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chem 110</title>
      <link>/syllabi/chem110</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Description</h2>
<p>
  The purpose of this course is to provide you with an introduction to atomic
  and molecular structure as well as molecular properties. We will also discuss
  general principles of reactions including stoichiometry and some
  thermodynamics. The long-term goal of this course is to get you to begin
  thinking of chemistry in your everyday life. You should begin noticing that
  chemistry is everywhere: it is in the foods we eat, the ingredients in our
  soaps, and the reason flowers and leaves have specific colors. I encourage you
  to send me anything that you find interesting about chemistry including
  videos, pictures, or websites.
</p>
<h2>Objectives</h2>
<p>At the end of the course, students will be able to…</p>
<ul>
  <li>Define key terms and concepts in chemistry</li>
  <li>
    Explain how atomic and molecular structure relates to macroscopic
    (observable) properties of matter
  </li>
  <li>
    Define the various forms of energy, explain how energy interacts with
    matter, and be able to calculate the energy changes associated with chemical
    and physical processes
  </li>
  <li>
    Apply chemistry concepts to solve mathematical problems on homework, problem
    sets, and exams
  </li>
  <li>
    Describe the chemistry behind phenomena in everyday life (i.e. why water is
    a liquid)
  </li>
</ul>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    PSU-E Chem 110: Structure and Properties (eBook, access codes available only
    through PSU Bookstore, ordering info here:
    <a href="http://sites.psu.edu/chem110wc/course-materials/" target="_blank"
      >http://sites.psu.edu/chem110wc/course-materials/</a
    >
    [a printed copy is available for purchase at the bookstore, but it does not
    include required in-text problems and interactive figures.]
  </li>
  <li>Scientific calculator (non-programmable)</li>
  <li>Video recording capabilities such as a smartphone or webcam</li>
  <li>Photo or scanning capabilities</li>
</ul>
<h2>Course Schedule</h2>
<table>
  <th>Week</th>
  <th>Topic(s)</th>
  <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>
      Course Overview<br />Introduction to Atomic Structure<br />The Mole, Ions
      & Molecules<br />Introduction to Energy
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>
      Light and Spectroscopy<br />Line Spectra & Bohr Model<br />Quantum Numbers
      and Orbitals
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>Electron Configuration<br />Periodic Properties</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Intro to Molecules<br />Molecular Formulas and % Composition</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>
      Ionic Compounds<br />Covalent Compounds & Bond Polarity<br />Lewis
      Structures & Formal Charge
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>
      Resonance<br />Exceptions to the Octet Rule<br />Electron Domain Geometry
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Molecular Geometry & Polarity<br />Hybridization<br />Pi bonding</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>Organic Molecules<br />Functional Groups & IM Forces</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>
      IM Forces & Phase Changes<br />Heating Curves<br />Vapor Pressure, Phase
      Diagrams, Liquid Properties
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>
      Solution Process<br />Electrolytes<br />Solubility (of solids and liquids)
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>11</td>
    <td>Concentration<br />KMT, Gas Laws</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>12</td>
    <td>
      Ideal Gases<br />Real Gases, Solubility of Gases<br />Chemical Reactions,
      Ionic Equations
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>13</td>
    <td>
      Classes of Reactions, Oxidation Number<br />Stoichiometry, Limiting
      Reactant, Percent Yeild<br />Reaction Calculations, Combustion Analysis
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>14</td>
    <td>Reaction Enthalpies<br />Calorimetry</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>15</td>
    <td>Hess's Law & Heats of Formation<br />Bond Dissociation Energies</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>Skills Check (~2%)</h2>
<p>
  The skills check is an opportunity to review topics from high school chemistry
  that will be used in CHEM 110. There are two parts to each of the five topics,
  aptly named “Part A” and “Part B.” Each part is a quiz with 5-7 questions and
  a 20-minute time limit. In Part A, you may take the quiz as many times as you
  like. Once you are confident in the skill, you can take Part B up to three
  times. Only the highest score in each part will be recorded. (Everyone can
  earn 100%!!!!) Your average percent score on all 10 quizzes (5 skills, two
  parts each) will be your grade on the skills check. For example, if you earn
  an 80%, you would earn 12 of 15 points.
</p>
<h2>Midterm Exams (~13%)</h2>
<p>
  There will be four (4) 50-minute midterm exams given over the course of the
  semester. Exams will focus on material covered since the last exam; however,
  you are still responsible for information presented previously. If you read
  your lecture notes & the eBook and solve the recommended problems, you will be
  able to anticipate the exam questions; all concepts could make multiple
  appearances. The exams will consist of short answer questions and open-ended
  problems. Some questions may be multiple choice. Stay tuned to announcements
  on the format.
</p>
<h2>Final Exam (~26%)</h2>
<p>
  A cumulative final exam will be given during the week of December 11. The exam
  window will be announced later in the semester. The final exam will be
  proctored remotely just as the midterm exams.
</p>
<h2>Homework Sets (~8%)</h2>
<p>
  There will be 15 graded homework sets (4 points each) throughout the semester.
  One assignment will be due every week. On most occasions homework will be
  graded solely based on completion and effort. On several randomly selected
  occasions, however, one randomly selected problem from the homework assignment
  will be graded for 2 points based on correctness. On those occasions,
  completing the rest of the homework assignment is worth an additional 2
  points, graded based on completeness and effort. Homework sets will be
  available on Canvas and are due by submitting a file in the Canvas assignment
  each Tuesday by 11:59 pm. There will be no late homework accepted. The lowest
  homework score will be dropped at the end of the term.
</p>
<p>
  Other assignments, such as an eBook Scavenger Hunt (7 points on Canvas) will
  be included in this category. If you earn 85% or more of the available
  homework points, you will earn all 60 points in the category! If you earn
  fewer than 85% of the possible points, you will receive a proportionally lower
  score. No extra credit results from accumulating a score of more than 85% of
  the points.
</p>
<h2>Participation (13%)</h2>
<p>
  Participation in class will come in three forms: attending a weekly
  recitation, answering the guiding questions, and interactions in ELMS/Piazza.
  More information on each type of participation is described below.
</p>
<h2>Weekly Recitation</h2>
<p>
  Recitations are one-hour sessions led by a pair of learning assistants via
  Zoom videoconferencing. Recitation is an opportunity to participate actively
  in problem solving and to ask questions about the material. Students will be
  assigned a recitation session according to their availability as indicated by
  a “When is Good” poll (sent to students via email prior to the start of
  classes). There will be 5-7 students in each recitation session. To be
  prepared for recitation, you should bring a copy of the recitation worksheet
  (available on ELMS), a copy of the Periodic Table and datasheet, and a
  scientific calculator. There will be 14 recitations (they will begin in week
  2). If you attend 12 of the 14 sessions, you will earn 4 all 30 points. Each
  absence beyond the first two will result in a three-point (10%) reduction of
  your recitation grade.
</p>
<h2>Guiding Questions</h2>
<p>
  Each week, there will be 2-3 “Guiding Question Sets” meant to assess your
  comprehension of the course content (reading and/or videos). These will be
  available in Canvas (also linked in ELMS) and due each Friday at 11:59 pm. If
  you earn an 85% or higher on the guiding question sets, you will receive all
  40 points available in the category. If you earn fewer than 85% of the
  possible points, you will receive a proportionally lower score. No extra
  credit results from accumulating a score of more than 85% of the points
</p>
<h2>Interactions</h2>
<p>
  Interactions include watching videos, answering embedded h5p questions in
  ELMS, and posting questions or answers to Piazza. Behind-the-scenes click data
  for users can be tracked and will be counted for this portion of the
  participation grade. We will use Piazza as a class forum/chatroom for asking
  and answering questions about the course. You can ask and answer questions
  here, which will be monitored by the TAs, LAs, and instructor. Please direct
  your questions here before e-mailing. You will be able to ask and answer
  anonymously if you wish. The beauty of Piazza is that the entire class can
  benefit from the questions and answers. More information on enrolling and
  etiquette for using will be provided during the semester. Any personal
  inquiries can be addressed by email (see below). If you interact with at least
  85% of the course content in ELMS and make a minimum of five (5) posts to
  Piazza, you will earn all 30 points in the category. If you interact with less
  than 85% of the content, you will receive a proportionally lower score.
</p>
<h2>Extra Credit (~1%)</h2>
<p>
  There will be several opportunities to earn up to a maximum of 8 extra credit
  points over the course of the semester. Opportunities will be announced as
  they come up. The number and type of assignment are at the discretion of the
  instructor.
</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabi/chem110</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 15:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>